Hello, I'm your host David Bernard. My
guest today is John Gruber, rockin tour,
Apple afficionado, podcast host, and
sole proprietor of Daring Fireball. On
the podcast, I talk with John about the
fascinating 40-year history of Apple's
developer relations, how almost going
bankrupt in the '9s shaped today's
control focused approach, and why we
might need an App Store 3.0 reset. Hey
John, thanks so much for coming back on
the podcast.
>> Well, you've been on my show. I hope to
have you on my show again soon. So, it's
the least I can do. I'm happy to be
here.
>> So, today I want to talk Apple
Kremlinology,
which I think is maybe a a great term. I
just threw it out there. Apple is such a
unique organization that a and for most
developers it's like our most important
partner and I'm doing air quotes for
those listening on the podcast and I
don't think a lot of people understand
Apple and I think a lot of how people
interact with Apple what they think of
Apple is shaped by just not
understanding them which is maybe on
Apple right but that's that's what I
wanted to talk about today was you know
better understanding Apple and I think
of of all the people to have this
conversation with. It's going to be
really fun to have it with you.
>> I appreciate that and only because and I
hate to flatter myself. Uh I really do.
I really do. I try to stay as humble as
possible. I feel like that's what keeps
me in the game. But like understanding
Apple to me is maybe, you know, one of
the top three things I have. you know, I
I really, you know,
>> and there's always been an intuitive,
oh, I love this company vibe fit, you
know, and some other rolls of the dice
of the way my life could have worked
out. Surely on many of the other rolls
of the dice, I end up working at Apple
for some amount of time, possibly a very
short amount of time because every time
every time I've ever had a job in my
life where I actually am not
self-employed, has not lasted all that
long. So, probably not long. But my one
of my earliest memories, I think it was
either fifth or sixth grade, which was
like early ' 80s, probably like 1983,84.
I just remember reading a story about
Apple computer and I knew at the time
that I liked Apple computers better than
other companies computers and I loved
computers but I remember reading a story
about the company and and reading that
all of the employees just show up to
work in sneakers and jeans and t-shirts
and that they wear clever t-shirts and
they make every time they start a new
project the first job is to print up
t-shirts for the team for the new
project and then they wear them to
And I remember thinking like that's
awesome cuz I don't want to wear a
freaking suit and tie to work. And I
remember telling my dad this and my dad
telling me, "John, there is no way that
a major computer company lets the people
show up to work in jeans and t-shirts."
And I was like, "No, I'm telling you,
Dad. I read it in a magazine. It's
true."
>> That's awesome. And then not to flutter
myself, but while we're we we we should
have scripted this and and I should have
done this for you and you should have
done this for me, but I relied on chat
GPT pretty heavily to do research for
this show because I wanted to go really
in depth in the history of Apple and
their relationships with developers. And
last night, I'm getting through my notes
and uh chat GPT says three of the
prominent voices in app store related
topics are John Gruber,
Ben Thompson, and David Bernard.
And I don't know if it knew it was me
and was like freaking trying to flatter
me or whatever, but you know, I mean,
similar to you, in a way that the app
store is something I'm I'm unreasonably
passionate about like like in a I have a
an emotional attachment to the App Store
and care so deeply about it. in in in
part and you and I have discussed this.
I was a recording engineer and I knew
that was kind of a dead end as far as
having a family and being able to
provide and stuff like that, but I was a
huge Apple nerd. So, I got a 17-inch
powerbook in 2003. So, my Apple journey
begins a little later. I mean, I used
them in college and I played with a
original Mac in the 80s, but my real
kind of Apple fanboyism started in like
2002, 2003. So, I jumped right into the
app store in 2008, thinking, okay, this
is an opportunity to like build a real
career that's going to provide for my
family and it did. I'm 17 years into
owning an app business and I care so
deeply about the store and then also
care so deeply about Apple. And so
everything we're going to talk about
today, it's like you being one of the
the the people who cares the most about
Apple who's outside Apple and me one of
the people who cares the most about the
app app store outside of Apple. I think
is the two right people to have this
kind of conversation and maybe we should
have had Ben on and to have a third
voice. But
>> there are certain things that I just
remember which years they were, you
know, and I just remember that 2007
iPhone, no App Store. 2008 App Store
comes out. 2009 it really takes off and
coincides really with the go- go years
of Twitter. And that's absolutely 100%
there's no confusion. I mean maybe you
sent me an email at daringfireball.net
or something. But where I remember
getting to know you was on Twitter, you
know, and I was just remember like it's
one of the great privileges of my
position doing what I do at Daring
Fireball where it's like, oh, I'm going
to get to know this guy, you know, and
and we'd at each other on Twitter about
app store issues, but I was like, this
guy, I could sense both your profound
enthusiasm for it and the way that it
was making you, it wasn't making you a
fanboy of the app store where no matter
what you wanted to say, oh, I love the
app store, so no matter what, I'm going
to I'm going to make my conclusion.
Whatever changes they make are great.
your enthusiasm was such that you're
like, I want to understand every single
thing about this to the deepest degree,
you know, and again, it's sort of like a
laziness where I'm like, oh, if I become
friends with this guy
and I've got like a a rolodex of people
who are experts on whatever, you know,
could be AppKit, could be UI Kit, could
be the App Store, could be, you know,
and you're like at the top of the list
for the App Store and have been since
like 2009 and probably should have been
since like 2008, but like I just
remember 2009
you were just like a key follow on
Twitter for app store related stuff and
it was such a fascinating time, you
know, like explosive just an explosive
time.
>> Well, and I was a Gubber fanboy and you
linking to my app in the fall of 2008, I
think, was in part a turning point. I
mean, there were like kind of key people
who kind of helped me along the way,
including people inside Apple. And I
remember vividly
>> that was it was the launcher app, right?
What was it called? No, no, no. This was
2008. You linked to my mileage logging
app. When the app store launched, there
was this terrible Windows phoneish,
horrible user interface, like no kind of
Mac or iOS interface paradigm, mileage
log that got there first, which is still
like eats me to this day. 17 years
later, I missed the launch of the App
Store because Apple did not approve my
developer account. And so a month later,
I released a mileage log that was like,
you know, we followed the iOS paradigms
and like and I mean looking back, I
don't ever feel like I have the best
taste, but I didn't have the it it was
brown and like it was not the prettiest
or most but it was iOS like we used the
paradigms of iOS. We we built a native
app and so you linked to that in the
fall of 2008 and it was it was a a
turning point.
>> Well, I'm I'm happy. I remember that and
that was the other thing that I remember
about you is it wasn't just that you
were obsessive about the app store is
that you actually had skin in the game
and that you clearly again I'm not just
trying to butter you up here but no but
there there there was at that time at
the very highest level when they first
announced the iPhone and said hey and
underneath it was like one of the it
wasn't called a bento box at the time
they did the slides in a different style
but at Steve Jobs original introduction
They they had a bunch of things on a
slide and they said Coco that everything
Apple had done for the original iPhone
before the iPhone before the app store
before they announced you know famously
it took them several months before they
said okay we're going to do an SDK but
they said you know that they were using
Coco there's like a 5minute podcast
Merlin man did at Macworld Expo talking
to me and Jason Snell the day of the
keynote on the floor of the you know it
was like a fiveminute interview with me
in Snell by Merlin man and Snell and I
were like, you know, Apple didn't say
much about this Coco thing, but you
know, presumably at some point, you
know, it's just probably not ready yet.
They're going to open up APIs and this
is going to be huge. I mean, this was
like hours after the keynote when we
were still euphoric about the whole
thing cuz everybody, you know, was sort
of looking forward to just an iPod
phone, right? And it was so much more.
You know, it felt like my mind had
gotten significantly bigger during the
keynote, like my brain had grown because
the the realm of possibility of personal
computing was suddenly much larger than
I thought. But in that initial moment,
most developers were thinking was, well,
that's fantastic if they're Coco APIs.
And you know, UI kit slightly different
than AppKit, but every single AppKit
going back to next developer I know
looked at the initial UI kit APIs and
was like, "Oh, all right. This is
different, but I know this. This is very
familiar. But the idea that developers
had was how do you take ideas that are
good Mac apps and put them on the phone
and for many apps that was a great idea
in Apple itself did that right Safari
mail how do you take mail and make a
version that fits on the phone but the
opportunity that I think people Mac
developers didn't think of right away is
what sort of ideas only make sense for a
phone a little pocket 3 3.5 in screen
device that's with you all the time that
wouldn't didn't make sense on a Mac. And
like a mileage tracker is exactly that
sort of idea. That's what I remember
hitting me about that app in 2008. Like,
oh, this would be stupid on a Mac,
right? What are you going to do? Take
your MacBook or or PowerBook? I forget
what I guess they were MacBooks by 2008,
but what are you going to do? Take a
laptop with you in your car everywhere
and log your gas and mileage? No. But
for something that would replace what
you would have done in a pocket
notebook, that's a perfect idea.
Obviously, people want this, you know,
and that that's where I feel like you
were ahead of me and I'm like, I got to
follow this guy because he's thinking
about things that are phone first,
>> right?
>> Yeah. Well, enough negleing. I'm I'm
blushing,
>> but I I appreciate all of that. And
again, just the the perfect person to
have this kind of conversation with,
which I've I've wanted to have this
conversation for a while in service of
the community of in my day job at
RevenueCat, and I do still build apps on
the side. So, I'm still an indie
developer. I I was looking at my
LinkedIn the other day and 17 years at
Contrast and still going strong, still
running my weather app on the side and
stuff. So, at my day job at RevenueCat,
I interface with a ton of developers and
a lot of them don't care one lick about
Apple. In fact, I mean, the growing
hostility people who've never built an
app before will have, you know, book an
office hours call with me and say,
"Screw Apple." You know, screw them in
and their 30%. Like, they just have
there's no care for Apple as a company
or the the products or anything like
that. Um, and so I wanted to do this
podcast to kind of give some of that
history. I was actually thinking as I
was preparing these notes like it it's
almost a book at some point, you know,
that the history of the app store and
how it shaped the world. I mean, so many
decisions that Apple made big and small
literally did shape how things happen.
And we'll we'll get into some of that,
but I wanted to step all the way back.
And again, in doing the research for
this over the weekend, I saw something
that that really surprised me and and I
think I kind of knew this, but I hadn't
seen the numbers and that is that the
three top executives at Apple whose
teams work on the app store. So, I think
maybe and and Apple is famously
secretive about who does what and who
reports to who and those kind of things,
but from my understanding,
>> they're secretive about everything,
baby.
>> Everything. Yeah. Yeah. something like
90% of the people who interface with
developers in the app store who work on
the app store report up to three
executives. Greg Joyak who joined Apple
in 1986.
>> Yeah. Like I think right out of college
at the University of Michigan and went
right to Apple.
>> Phil Schiller who joined Apple in 1987
and Eddie Q who joined Apple in 1989.
And so to really understand Apple and
how they interact with developers and
how they perceive the developer
community, you really do have to go all
the way back to the 1980s when these
three key executives joined and started.
And each of them have their different
role in developer relations over time.
But going back to that 1984 release of
the Mac and these early days of
developer relations between Apple and
developers, I think is so fascinating.
And one of the things again I didn't
even I knew but like seeing it again in
in black and white just how instrumental
Microsoft was in those early days to
Apple that two years ahead of the 1984
release of the Mac, Microsoft had agreed
to build products for this new platform.
And then specifically, and again, never
heard this before, but Bill Gates was
like kind of an Apple fanboy in some of
the early days before they got like
really contentious. And I I read this
like history piece about kind of the
history of Apple that said Gates would
show up to events, Mac World and other
events with Macintosh shirts. Like he
would wear a Macintosh I mean, can you
even imagine Bill Gates in the 80s
wearing Macintosh T-shirts? It's like it
was just such a different era. But then
over time, developer relations started
to get a bit contentious. What do you
remember? I mean, you were gosh, like 6
8 10 at the time when all this happened,
and I was like five, but we've both read
a lot about the history. So, what do you
recall? And then what do you remember
from having read up on all this?
>> Too young to have experienced those
years extemporaneously. Um, but from
what I've read, one of the key
superpowers that Gates had and sort of,
and I think it's true, I think it's, you
know, I don't, this is not an original
observation, but no matter how big and
no matter even, I mean, I guess
eventually after, you know, when you get
closer to like 50 years, which, you
know, Apple and Microsoft are at, but
maybe closer to a century after entire
original generations have clearly all
died off, it fades away. But all
companies in all fields are just infused
with the personalities of their
founders. And one of the things that
Gates infused in Microsoft was an
amazing willingness or just just natural
ability. I don't even think it was
something he did purposefully. I think
it's just the way his mind worked. is he
was always thinking what could be and
was not attached to the way things were.
the whole name Microsoft, you know, that
the whole idea, the revolution of the
company was, hey, we could make a
company, this was him and Paul Allen,
that just focuses on software and had no
plans in those early days to make their
own computer. And all of the action in
the late '7s at that moment of the PC
revolution, the late '7s and the early
80s was on the companies making
computers, Apple and Commodore and Texas
Instruments, you you name it. IBM once
they made the the PC and Microsoft's key
insight was, hey, software is incredibly
valuable. And at the time, that idea
alone was revolutionary. It was
absolutely revolutionary because
everybody else thought the only thing
that matters is computers and computers
were all absurdly expensive. You know,
you know, just look at the memory that
was in those computers. The Commodore 64
was called the 64 not because it was
64-bit, but because it had 64 kilobytes
of RAM, right? That that was the 64.
And, you know, it wasn't cheap cheap.
And the idea was software. You just, you
know, copy. It was just ones and zeros.
you could just make copies. And the idea
that no, no, software is worth paying
for was a revolution. And I think that's
why Gates could have such incredible
enthusiasm for something like some other
company's computer because everything
they did was for somebody else's
computer. They didn't make computers and
they didn't really have a platform. And
so I think Gates recognized early that
Apple made better computers and that
they were on to something. And he
clearly from a very you know from the
outset had the mindset of like the
complete opposite of I forget his name
but the 1960s era IBM CEO who said I I
think there's a a market in the world
for six or seven computers
you know cuz the thinking in that era
was well the US military will want one
maybe like the US IRS and there'll be
like one great supercomput for
iversities to share and whereas Gates
was really thinking early on oh no there
should be computers in every house but
he wasn't thinking that Microsoft would
own a platform but then when the
opportunity came with DOSs and they saw
the sort of the opportunity they had by
owning MS DOSs and being the company
that provided it changed their thinking
completely you know to instead of oh
we'll make software for anybody's
computer we're going to make a platform
and we'll still make some software ware
for other platforms, but we really want
to steer everybody to our platform even
though we don't make the computers.
>> One of the interesting footnotes in this
as well is that Apple had a similar idea
of like we're building this platform, we
need to make sure there's software on
it. And so they built Macrite, Mac
Paint, Mac Draw, and a bunch of other
apps. And again, something I didn't
realize until doing all this research
was that in 1986, they stopped bundling
those because it was competitive with
third party developers. And man, I mean,
these days with Sherlocking and Apple
building an app for everything. I mean,
even most recently building an invite
app like building a sports app like you
know, Apple has over the last, you know,
17 years of the app store gone deeper
and deeper and further and further into
competing directly with third party
developers. But back here in the 80s,
they were like, "Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
We don't want to squash the potential
for third party developers to to build
for this platform that we have." So
these apps that we built for our own
platform that we have previously
bundled. I mean, again, at some point,
maybe when Schiller or Jaws or one of
these guys retires, you know, we'll do
this again and get the inside scoop on
like some of the deeper thinking behind
this, but they stopped bundling. And
then in 1987, they spun all those apps
off into ClariS, a subsidiary of Apple,
to have them at little bit more of an
arms length specifically to like not
interfere with third party developers.
And it's so fascinating to go all the
way back to the 80s and see such a
different Apple that they recognize the
power of developers in the platform and
were actively doing things at that time
to make sure they didn't compete. They
didn't make it a non-starter for people
to to build these kind of apps for the
Macintosh platform which is just
fascinating
>> and it was about a decade I would say
like maybe 86 87 and those are the years
where I was there as a teenager into
college and uh for like 86 to 95 96 or
so was like the decade where Apple was
very handsoff about first party apps and
it made sense I mean And one of the
areas of contention, it's sort of like a
heartbreak and I forget the exact
details. I know Andy Herzfeld's
wonderful, wonderful, I think there's a
story about it on folklore.org, but you
can look it up. But there were two
basics, you know, the basic programming
language for the Mac in the very
early8s. And Apple Basic was much better
and could let you do Macintosh like
things like pop open a dialogue box
which you know you think like well of
course you know why would you want to
have a programming environment for the
Mac that couldn't pop open a dialogue
box but that was revolutionary at the
time and Microsoft had their basic and
as like a let's keep Microsoft happy
Apple sort of squashed their own
in-house basic which was a much better
programming environment for the
Macintosh so as not to step on the toes
of Microsoft Basic, which was more of a
oh character-based sort of text
interface basic where you could write
the same Microsoft Basic program and run
it on the Mac and run it on any other
computer that had Microsoft Basic. And
that's just one example of that sort of
thinking and the sort of thing that led
them to spin off the initial which they
sort of had to do again because nobody
knew how to write these graphical user
interface programs. It often comes up
and people, you know, you have to like
Google the images and to believe it. But
the original Macintosh keyboard didn't
have arrow keys because they wanted to
force developers and users to use the
mouse as opposed to almost all other
computers at the time didn't even have
mice, right? So there was the Macintosh
which had a mouse and other computers
which had no pointer in interface, just
a keyboard interface. So like you'd be
like, "What do you want to do in the
computer?" and it would present a text
menu and you'd use arrow keys to go up
and down. I want to open existing file
down. I want to create a new file. Down.
I want to manage my files. Up, up, down,
left, right. So to force developers to
make programs that were mouse driven,
mouse pointer driven. Apple didn't even
put arrow keys on the original Macintosh
keyboard, which imagine the frustration
editing text now. So if you wanted to
like you could like backspace there was
a delete key but if you wanted to go
back a word or two you had to go take
your hands off the keyboard go to the
mouse and click where you wanted to go
but I understand why that didn't last
but I also understand the thinking at
the time to break people's habits
because as much as they thought this is
a computer for the rest of us which was
their slogan and this will be the way
that most people in the future learn to
use computers right now the market is
people who already know how to use
computers, but what they know from the
existing computers isn't the way this
computer works. And so they had to make
apps like Macr Wright and Mac Paint and
Mac Draw. And then like 2 years in,
they're like, uh, we're kind of
squashing the market. What we really
need is a thriving third party market,
so let's go sort of go hands off. And
then for the next decade, the Mac really
didn't have many firstparty programs.
You know, if you just went to the store
and bought a brand new Macintosh in 1991
or '92,
>> you got like text edit or or it was
called simple text at the time. There
were very few apps that were built in.
There was no built-in contacts app. You
didn't have all these things that you
would think, oh, how do you have a
computer without an address book? Well,
the idea was that whole thing was a
third party opportunity.
>> Yeah. And th this is a great example of
why I wanted to have this conversation.
And and maybe we'll kind of pull on some
of these threads as as we go through,
one thing to understand about Apple and
how they operate today is that they've
had success in doing those sorts of
things. And so when you look at Apple TV
that famously launched and Apple tried
to get people to develop games for it,
but you could only use the Apple remote.
And it was Apple, as with the keyboard,
not having arrow keys, it was, we don't
want people to require a gaming
controller to build games, so we're
going to force them to use remote. And
games sucked. And I was so pissed at
Apple. It took him what, like three or
four years to finally enable controller
support. And by that time, it was just
so clear that Apple TV was not going to
be a gaming platform. Maybe could have
been more of a gaming platform had they
done it. Maybe it was the right choice,
whatever. And then look at the Vision
Pro two years ago. I was so frustrated
that Apple didn't release, you know,
motion track controllers like what you
have on the MetaQuest. But why did they
do that? Goes all the way back to 1984
and not having the arrow keys. It was,
hey, we're introducing a new user
interface paradigm, a new user
experience, and we want to force
developers to build apps that use hand
gestures and eyetracking and not
controllers. Now, you know, 2 years
later, they just announced at WWC that
PlayStation VR controller support
Envision Pro, but this is, you know, 2
years after the fact, and I was so
frustrated 2 years ago, but this is one
of those things when you look back, you
you better understand why they make the
decisions they make. They have a long
history of making those kind of
decisions going all the way back to the
80s and forcing developers into the path
that they think is best for the
platform. It's just so fascinating. I
keep repeating it. I'm more bullish on
Vision OS as a platform than most
commentators. And I keep drawing the
analogy to the original Macintosh. The
original Macintosh in 1984, I know the
number off the top of my head cuz I
bring it up all the time. It was $2,500,
which inflation adjusted is like give or
take right now like $7,200.
You know, there was only one config.
There was no option to get more RAM.
There was no storage. You used floppy
drives. So $2,500. It was 7,200
equivalent today. About twice the cost
of a Vision Pro. Very expensive. It sold
so poorly and so under their
expectations that it was the impetus for
driving Jobs out of the company. And in
the whole people don't know the history
like how in the world did Apple kick
Steve Jobs out of the company the real
reasons were mostly personality
conflicts you know and that yes of
course he did not work well when there
was somebody else John Scully from Pepsi
as the CEO who Jobs the founder
ostensibly reported to of course Jobs
did not work well as anything but the
CEO and that's ultimately the reason but
in terms of going to the board and
having reasons other than this guy's a
pain in my ass to force him out. The
sales of the Mac were the and again it
was expensive and and Apple couldn't
really afford the fact that it was a bit
of a flop in 1984 1985.
But the PC press of the time, you know,
took it as, hey, this whole graphical
user interface thing, it's clever, but
it's a gimmick. This isn't how real
computer users want to use a computer.
Nobody wants to take their hands off the
keyboard and use a mouse all the time.
It's a waste of memory to be drawing all
these windows and stuff like this. That
was all proven wrong. The Mac was the
right idea for the future of personal
computing. But it needed at least four
or five years before you're like, "Holy
this is like a thriving platform
that's revolutionizing certain
industries, you know, like desktop
publishing."
>> Yeah. And as a 40 almost 50 year old
company, I guess next year's 50 years,
somewhere around there. Apple's patience
is remarkable. This is another thing
that I continually get wrong and that I
think a lot of people get wrong.
>> 100% agree on the Vision Pro.
>> It is a phenomenal piece of hardware. It
is an incredible platform for
experimenting with the future,
even if it's flawed and even if there
are problems. But Apple's patient, you
know, and clearly they have AR stuff in
the labs that, you know, Cook and others
have played with. There's been reporting
recently about all uh Tim Cook thinks
about is getting to this, you know, AR
glasses future, whatever it might be.
And the Vision Pro is that first step
along the way. And Apple is very
patient. As much as people pan it, as
few units as they sold, even if it's
been less successful as they internally
hope for, they are nothing if not a
patient company that's going to keep
plugging away at these things because
look how it turned out for the Mac. Like
you said, it took four or five years.
Well, I mean, we're two years into the
Vision Pro. like they've got time and
they've got cash to wait around and they
they've got the experience of building
these platforms over decades, not making
sure something is a hit, you know, in in
months and days. This is only based on
observation but I think it's you know I
I I almost see like how can somebody
refute this is that their thinking is
basically if their projection of where a
hit AR/VR
let's just put aside whether the first
hit product in the category will be AR
or VR but it'll probably be AR right
like VR is just too weird where where my
definition of the difference the broad
difference here is if the device is off
powered
Can you see anything or do you see
through glasses? Right? If it's glasses
that when the device is at 0% battery,
powered off, you still see through the
lenses, that's AR. And if it's like
Vision Pro where it's off, you it's like
blindfolds. That's VR. It's probably AR,
but let's just say, doesn't matter. put
that aside that it'll take till around
to have a product at a price and a
feature set and a battery life that's
compelling to explode in popularity and
that people will be like, I got to get
one of those. If it's 2030 when that's
going to come out, what's the right way
to approach the market? And I think the
people who are laughing at Vision Pro
and saying it's $3,500. Nobody's bought
one. There's I've only sold hundreds of
thousands, not even a million, whatever.
Apple should have waited until then to
release a product and then boom, here's
the first thing. And the iPhone was sort
of like that, right? And the iPhone was
like right out of the gate. Yes, it was
a little more expensive, but the first
iPhone was incredibly useful, totally
credible device. And I know it didn't
sell in great quantities compared to
today's numbers, but as somebody who
bought one, it was like, "Yeah, this is
real." And it's not like I've I'm buying
a product that hints at a future. The
Vision Pro is not like that. The Vision
Pro is not the iPhone in 2007. The
Vision Pro today is like a I don't like
calling it a dev kit, but it's like an
enthusiast kit, which includes
developers, but it's an enthusiast kit
that you spend a ridiculous amount of
money compared to like a MacBook Air,
right? You get a really good MacBook Air
for $1,000. So, you can get a really
good MacBook Air for like $1,300,
$1,400.
This is like three times, four times
more expensive and it's less essential
to people's lives than their iPhone,
which you can get a really good iPhone
for like $7, $800.
It's different than that. But is the
right strategy to wait until that
hardware is out in 2030 and then start
there with building a platform or is the
right strategy to start building a
platform around 2023, 2024.
And when that hardware is finally
available and there's a breakthrough in
the technology and the price and the
capabilities and the battery life that
you've got 5 years of ecosystem and
content behind it. All these complaints
again I I've complained too and I'm a
little surprised but you know they're
getting there just in terms of having
entertaining immersive content. the
things like the Bono video and the
adventure climbing mountains and all the
stuff that, you know, they've got some
stuff. You would think with their budget
that they could have more, but the idea
of, hey, if they're going to sell this
thing for all this money, shouldn't they
have more content available? Well, if
2030 is when they kind of think this is
going to explode, think of how much
content they're going to have in the
library by then. And I think that's what
they know. There are so many
similarities between this and the
Macintosh in 1984,
but there are also so many profound
differences, you know, because Apple is
so big and so pervasive in popular
culture and people's lives, and it
breeds a different sentiment towards the
company, which I think we're going to
continue talking about with developer
relations. But then on the other hand,
their profound almost unfathomable
financial success gives them the liberty
of saying, "We're going to make a 7-year
bet that costs a lot of money." Just in
terms of like the thousand or so
software engineers who work on vision
stuff, you know, inside the company,
we're going to make a profound bet to
build this out over half a decade so
that when the hardware is really there
for a mass market thing, we've got it.
We've already got the platform. We've
already got the UI paradigms nailed
down. We've got the input. We've got the
sensors. We're going to be there five
years ahead of time. It's a very
different way of thinking than a company
that is like sweating it out. Are we
still going to be in business two
quarters from now?
>> Yeah. And I think that's part of the
push back is that too many people,
especially in the press, continue to
expect every product Apple releases to
be the next iPhone. And the the iPhone
is just singular in history as a
consumer electronic device
>> that it was able to come out of the gate
as such an incredible useful day one
thing cuz even like and again I mean
this is why we're having this
conversation. You go back to 1984 the
$2500 which is $7,200 today or whatever
it is was not a daily driver. This is
like changing my life most productive
thing in the world. It was a nice to
have. It was an enthusiast. It was a,
you know, something to tinker with. And
maybe you find a few productivity things
here and there that it benefits. Apple
has done this decade after decade after
decade and they they have that long
vision. And again, going back to these
execs who've been around through it all,
it's like they've seen it happen and
they know it will happen and they know
it can happen. And to your point,
they're not under that pressure of like
the Vision Pro has to be the iPhone. It
doesn't have to be the iPhone. We've
done this, you know, 10 times before
with different products with
transitioning from Power PC to Intel
with, you know, early days of iMac and
it becoming a consumer hit. That wasn't
even like the massive smash hit, you
know, compared to the iPhone. And so
it's like they know how to build
platforms over decades and not over
months and years that everybody else
expects it to happen. So the one
difference and it is almost the same
thing but along a different vector where
I said about Gates and the way that
Gates instilled in Microsoft a sort of
flexibility in thinking like hey what's
the opportunities right now and I do
think I think Satia Nadella's era as CEO
embodies that you know where I feel like
he came in and was like you know what we
don't have to be all about Windows
Windows Windows we can go into more of a
cloud first mindset and look at where
they are financially and you know in
cloud services and stuff. It's been a
great deal for them but that they got
their institutional fortitude is once we
have a hit we will latch on to it and
try to stick with it and ride it all the
way down. And that was the whole mindset
with Windows. Windows everywhere and
they're going to put Windows on your TV
settop box and Windows phone, right? And
they were trying to make smartphones
years before the iPhone. And it
literally they had a start menu in the
lower left corner. It looked like
Windows 95 but on a phone. And it wasn't
running Windows apps, but it was a
mindset of bringing the Windows
mentality. Whereas Apple's mindset led
by Steve Jobs was let's start from
scratch. And as much as they wound up
using the Coco APIs and made UI kit, it
was only not because like that was a
starting point. It was like, okay, if
we're going to do this, maybe we could
fit a small version of the Mac kernel
onto this device and we'll build it. But
we're not going to have any
compatibility. You know, it's not going
to be called the Mac phone. We're not
going to have an Apple menu up in the
upper left corner. we're going to
rethink this whole thing from scratch.
Apple has this sort of if it's a new
form factor, we're going to start with a
new platform. And that's a very
different thinking. But at another
level, just in terms of its
capabilities, the reason the iPhone
could debut in 2007 as a totally
credible, you could buy one right now,
the first one, totally useful, is that
it's ultimately, and this is like the
unifying theme of the last 5 years of
dithering with me and Ben Thompson, is
that the the biggest marketing shame of
the entire industry is that we wasted
the term personal computer
>> on desktop and laptop. up computers in
1980 because the phone is ultimately the
personal computer and that's where
everything was heading from the Apple 1
in 1977
until 2007. Everything was heading
towards building something under $1,000
that fit in your pocket and it had a
interface that anybody could just use
and that the input was just poking at it
with your finger and it was all visual
and it had wireless connection to a
network that connected to the entire
world. It was so science fiction from
the perspective of 197879
and but within 30 years that's where
everything in those 30 years was
heading. So when it launched it was
really the culmination of what we've
called personal computers for 30 years
whereas vision pro is sort of like let's
do something all new and we have to sort
of start from scratch. It's going to be
way too expensive and heavy and limited
and the battery is going to be a pain in
the ass. But it's a totally new vector.
>> Yeah. Well, we've kind of gotten ahead
of ourselves. I I do I I want to go all
the way back to the 80s. Again, it's
important to kind of step through the
the history of these developer relations
of what brought us even to the iPhone.
So, I'll speed through this. You you and
I could talk for 5 hours, but I I don't
think we should turn this into a 5-hour
podcast.
So, I'll speed through a little bit of
this, but going all the way back to the
80s, PageMaker was a huge turning point.
a third party app. Uh, you know, some
people have credited it as saving the
Mac platform that it was so important to
digital publishing and and this is where
as a platform
apps can revolutionize your platform.
When you've built a platform and
hardware and third party developers go
nuts on it, they build new things and do
things that you would have never done as
a firstparty software closed ecosystem.
um it's only you know Apple and the Mac
and we're the only ones building for it.
you get this entire ecosystem of people
building new things and pagemaker was
one of those things that became so
integral to the digital publishing world
that it's credited as a thirdparty app
for saving the whole Apple Mac platform
and then you get Illustrator for Mac in
' 87 you get Photoshop in 1990 and
during this time I think Apple really
recognizes that power of developers guy
Kawasaki joined around that time I
forget exactly I think he may have
joined for the the 1984 Mac, but he was
the first software evangelist and
developer evangelist. And in again in
doing research for this and reading up
on some of the history of this, I
realized just how much a debt of
gratitude in some ways I owe to Guy
Kawasaki for me having a job today at
Revenue is that he like this whole like
developer advocacy and you know people
who aren't technical but are or you know
I mean I'm mildly technical but really
can promote these platforms. It goes all
the way back to the 80s and Guy Kawasaki
and like and Apple being so enthusiastic
for thirdparty developers.
>> I know Guy a little. I feel like I
should know him better. I feel like he
sort of left this racket right around
the time that I was becoming more
prominent in this industry. But I've met
him a few times. But I've read his books
and like the the Macintosh way.
>> It's a great book if you can find a copy
of it. When I joined Barebones Software,
I worked at Barebones, the BBEdit
company, from 2000 to 2002. It was the
only mandatory reading before it was
like the entire employee onboarding
process was you have to read Guy
Kawasaki's the Macintosh way. But
arguably it was the Apple way, you know,
and and at the time though because it
was the only successful platform Apple
had, the Macintosh and Apple were easily
conflated. But I think that what Guy
Kawasaki really crystallized was the
intersection of developers, users, and
the platform maker, you know, and that
combined the three could form a cohesive
hole that everything, you know, and and
formed a u like a flywheel where it just
kept benefiting everybody where users
are happy and they're buying the devices
which helps the platform maker and that
the more devices the platform maker
makes, the bigger the market is for
third-party developers. And so third
party developers make more and invest
more in the platform and make more
innovative software that makes users
like, "Oh my god, look what PageMaker
can do. Holy crap." And then the users,
you know, buy more of the, you know, and
it just keeps going and going and that
>> sounds a lot like the iPhone.
>> Yeah. And I think that the other thing
that Guy Kawasaki really sort of
crystallized was the idea that you could
be an important serious player
professionally in this field without
being a programmer, you know, or a
designer even. You could be like a
professional user. I'm a writer and I
have a computer science degree from
college from long ago. So, you know, I
more technical than most users, but I
get that mindset where what kind of what
I wanted to be was a professional user
by being an enthusiast and learning how
all everything works. And that was his
evangelism. You know, it wasn't
evangelism in the sense of evangelizing
a religion based on faith. It was more
like a religion based on practical
advantages. Like, hey, learn how to do
these things. learn how the actual
system works and you're going to have
superpowers compared to people who do
the same thing as you who don't
understand how these computers work. One
person can do the work of 10 people, you
know, with a Macintosh. And it was true.
You know,
>> I saw that guy has been doing the rounds
on podcast. You should definitely have
him on your podcast at some point. That
that'd be one I would love to listen to.
You and you and Guy talking through this
>> for two hours. you know, we're we're
kind of breezing over it in like five
minutes here, but I think uh it would be
a fascinating listen for you and Guy to
kind of talk through that in more
detail, but we did want to keep moving.
So, so that was the the kind of 80s and
into the early 90s. But then what
happened in the '9s, I think, is kind of
pivotal to Apple's relationship with
developers is that in the '9s, and and
you know this better than I, so you can
fill in the details here, but you know,
hardware sales started to tank. things
started to get really rocky for Apple
and they got to this point where
third-party developers had so much power
over Apple that if Adobe wasn't updating
their apps on the Mac platform and
simultaneously the Windows platform had
taken off at that point where they were
probably I assume making way more money
on the Windows platform. was kind of the
platform to be on during that time, but
Apple desperately needed those third
party developers to continue building
for the platform to keep the platform
sustainable. And that all kind of
culminated in 1997 with the famous, you
know, Steve Jobs standing in an
auditorium with a giant screen of Bill
Gates behind him and Microsoft saving
Apple. And and again, you know, people
who haven't studied the history or been
around and not old men like you and I
couldn't even fathom that Microsoft
saved Apple. Had had Microsoft not done
that, Apple may have gone probably would
have gone bankrupt. So fill in some of
the gaps there. What happened in the '9s
and how did Apple get into this
desperate point where third party
developers had so much power over them
needing Microsoft to save the company?
>> I think point one that gets overlooked a
lot in the years where Jobs was exiled
from Apple. Who knows what would have
happened. Maybe that was for the best
that he went and founded. You know, it
worked out or it worked out well for him
to go found Next, struggle to make Next
a thing, and then have Next and Apple. I
I always call it a reunification rather
than an acquisition because it really is
so obvious. I mean, Craig Federigi's
first job out of college was at Next,
right? And it's like he left for a
while, right? Scott Forsttoall. But
where Apple got lost in those years, one
of the ways and I think I I haven't seen
a lot of people or a lot of books focus
on it was the sort of mindset in the
early PC years,
a company would come out with a new
computer and the computer was the
platform effectively, right? And there
wasn't really this idea. There wasn't so
much of, you know, like you'd make the
Commodore 64 and then when Commodore
came out with the Commodore 128, I
forget if you could run Commodore 64
programs, but it was sort of a new
computer, you know, it was like, ah,
this is a different computer. And then
Commodore came out with uh AmIGGA. It's
sort of an overlooked thing in history,
and I know like the Panic guys were big
Amigga fans. And the AmIGGA had the
video toaster was doing digital video
editing way before any other computer
platform. It had some amazing
capabilities, but Commodore just
exemplifies it. You know, you Commodore
64 was a hit, then the 128, not so much
of a hit. and the Amigga, which was way
more capable, but that every couple of
years, the idea was there'd be like a
new thing and backwards compatibility
was like a maybe, you know, and it would
be like a mode, but basically you'd sort
of come out with an all new thing every
couple years as opposed to evolving a
platform over decades. It just didn't
enter Apple's mind. And so Apple had all
of these failed next generation, what's
going to come after the Macintosh things
in the late 80s and especially the early
'9s. Pink and Taligent. And it's all
confusing and it would take forever to
explain as opposed to what was an
operating system and what was a company
and what was a crossplatform. Like
Taligent was sort of a cross company
thing with IBM where it was in addition
to an operating system. they'd make a
new platform and the Power PC chip
architecture sort of came out of that
and there so it wasn't totally feudal
but but the idea wasn't to how do we
keep evolving the Macintosh it was what
comes after the Macintosh that's the
fundamental flaw and like the Newton you
know is laughed at in some ways and
other ways people are like oh man
they're sort of ahead you know like a
decade ahead of their time in terms of
like you know you'd have a handheld
thing in your hand with a touchcreen but
the most obvious problem with the Newton
was that something handheld like that
needs ubiquitous wireless networking and
there wasn't even Wi-Fi at the time, let
alone cellular. Palm Pilot was sort of
more of a hit, but mostly because it was
affordable and people like me, I had
one. I had a handspring visor and I
liked it. You know, in hindsight,
there's a lot of younger people who
probably, you know, vaguely have heard
of Palm Pilots, but it wasn't that big a
deal. You know, at the time people are
like, "Oh, the Palm Pilot is what Apple
should have made with the Newton." No,
because even the Palm Pilot really
wasn't that big of a hit and it didn't
have any staying power because it didn't
do networking. It didn't have a
connection to the internet, even Wi-Fi,
let alone cellular. That's really what a
handheld needed. But the other thing
about the Newton that was just as
important to its failure was it really
hardly related to the Macintosh at all.
There was like a Newton I forget what
it's called, Newton sync utility or
something and there you connect a serial
cable to your Mac and Newton. could sync
some things, but like I said earlier,
there was no contact app on the Mac from
Apple. So, like where did your Newton
contacts go? The Newton had a contacts
app because it was a personal digital
assistant. And they had all of these
things about like what comes after the
Macintosh when what they should have
clearly been thinking of is how do we
move the Macintosh forward? And
meanwhile, while Apple's core interest
and at the top level of the company was
interested on these big expensive all
failed next generation what comes after
the Macintosh, there were people at
Apple who were grinding away on the
Macintosh, putting out system 7 and then
system 7.1, system 75 and sort of
keeping the company alive financially
because that's an actual platform that
people were using and buying. And I
think at the highest level, Apple was
looking at that the way that the
Macintosh part of the company was
looking at the Apple 2 in the 80s,
right? And for most of those like mid to
late 80s, Apple was staying alive
financially through Apple 2 sales, not
Macintosh sales. And they were thinking
that's what the Macintosh is doing now,
and we'll get Pink or Copeland or
whatever this thing is. I Copeland was a
next generation Mac. That was where they
started to get it through their head
that oh what we really need to do is
keep the Mac alive and come up with
something. They just wasted half a
decade of great it was still explosive
new stuff coming out. The whole internet
thing happened in the midst of that
right where there was no internet to
speak of. I mean the internet existed
but it was like a university type thing
in 1991
and by 1993
four five it was like oh Netscape is a
huge thing you know in the meanwhile
Microsoft was doing the opposite with
Windows where they're like Windows one
nobody used nobody even heard of Windows
2 nobody used nobody heard of Windows 3
ah now people are using it instead of
DOSs but it was really clunky and awful
and they're like let's make a better one
let's make one that steals interface
ideas from next you where the buttons
and stuff look 3D and have grayscale.
And they were grinding away on making
the thing that was sort of a hit just a
little better every couple years. And
Apple just lost half a decade in that
period. And thankfully they had people
who were incrementally making the
Macintosh better, but then they'd sort
of painted themselves in a corner where
the Macintosh operating system, not to
get too super nerdy, but was still
fundamentally based on some assumptions
from the mid80s about how lowlevel all
software worked, you know, and the idea
of preemptive multitasking
where like a program crashing couldn't
possibly crash the whole computer
because it would just be the program.
Whereas the Macintosh was so low-level
and all programs sort of made some
low-level assumptions where they were
there was no kernel to speak of in
computer science terms in that classic
Mac OS and they were doing things with
low-level memory where like hey if
Internet Explorer froze up your whole
computer might just freeze and then you
had to like literally use the power
button on the hardware to restart it and
anything you had open that wasn't saved
was gone. In 1984,8586
that's the way a computer like the
Macintosh had to work. There was no
option to do preemptive multitasking and
have memory safe applications in that
era because of the constraints of the
hardware. But by like 199596
that was totally possible and it was
obviously the way it should be. But
there was no simple way to just say
that's how the next version of Mac OS is
going to work. and all of the existing
apps like Photoshop and Excel and
Microsoft Word will just work. There was
no way. It was too incompatible. And
that's what you were talking about
earlier where Apple was up against it
because the only reason the Macintosh
was thriving was because of these apps
from companies like and the big ones
were Adobe and Microsoft. And if their
existing apps didn't continue to work,
there was no way anybody was going to
upgrade to whatever they came up with no
matter what its technical capabilities.
And so then being back against the wall
and jobs having gone off to next and
built that next iteration, the next
revolution in computing, the foundation
for everything we do today was what Jobs
built at Next. They acquire Next in 96
and Jobs comes back and then that's what
leads up to this Microsoft committing to
the platform, investing money into
Apple. And then I wanted to read a quote
and this is going to be long and those
of you who really care can go back and
watch. There's a video of this is that
at WWDC197
there's a quote from Jobs. A developer
asked about open doc. So open I don't
you know all this but we we can skip
over the details of it because I think
the details are less important
>> but Apple decided to kill this
technology open doc
>> and a developer very frustrated goes up
to the mic at WWC during an open mic
session with Steve Jobs at WWC and 97
very frustrated why are you killing this
thing we've invested a lot of money into
it and I want to read the quote I kind
of jump around in the quote because it
would take 10 minutes to read but let me
read this quote from Steve Jobs because
I I think it's just so fascinating. I
know some of you spent a lot of time
working on stuff that we put a bullet in
the head of. I apologize. I feel your
pain. I wanted to get that in there cuz
can you imagine Apple in 2025
saying I apologize. I feel your pain.
And then and just the rest of this
>> I can imagine it but it would be very
surprising and I feel like that's
exactly what they could use. But yes.
>> Yeah. That's what we're going to get to
and that's why I wanted these quotes.
We'll come back to it maybe an hour from
now when we get deeper into the iPhone
stuff. So, continuing skipping around
the quote, but focusing is about saying
no. Focusing is about saying no. And
you've got to say no, no, no. And when
you say no, you piss off people. So, you
take your lumps. And Apple has been
taking their share of lumps for the past
six months in a very unfair way. And
it's been taking them, you know, like an
adult. And I'm proud of that, man. Steve
Jobs off the cuff. I miss that. I miss
that so much. And the result of that
focus is going to be some really great
products where the total is much greater
than the sum of the parts. So again,
that's missing a lot of context. It's
missing a lot of the actual quote. You
can go back and watch the video. I'll
put it in the show notes. But I just
thought that was so fascinating that
that Apple in 97 was at this point that
Steve Jobs of all people was there on
stage answering this kind of question
with a level of kind of humility and
self-awareness that hey developers are
so important. I feel your pain. I'm
sorry. I apologize. But then also
clearly
talking to the future of like, hey, this
is going to be hard, but we're building
towards something. And I included that
quote specifically for what you were
alluding to is that in this, you know,
40-year history with developers, there
have been moments like that where you
see a more open Apple, a more contrite
Apple, and that the success of the
iPhone has really changed the way I feel
like Apple does relate to developers.
And Apple has not had to take its lumps
in a good 20 or 30 years. Um, and has
not kind of had that level of kind of
forthrightness and humility with
developers when things do go sideways.
But, and this is where I think Ben
Thompson, you know, has said multiple
times on different podcasts and articles
he's written. I think some people inside
Apple view this and maybe these, you
know, those three top execs who've been
there this whole time and a lot of
people inside Apple, it felt
humiliating, not humble, and that this
was a period in their history that they
were so beholden to third party
developers and they never wanted to be
in that position again. They never
wanted to have to take lumps again. and
they never wanted to be on that verge of
bankruptcy. They they never wanted to
feel that pain and be humiliated like
that again. Versus like I go back and I
read this, I'm like, "Wow, like what a
great example of just, you know, how
much goodwill do you instill in
developers in the entire ecosystem by
speaking like that to developers?" The
first thing I'll say to that is that of
those three executives you've mentioned,
Eddie Q, Jaws, and Schiller, Schiller is
the exception where Schiller, I know you
probably know this, actually hasn't been
in Apple continuously since 1987 or
whatever. And in the early 90s, he was I
forget where else, but he ended up at
Macromedia, which was the company behind
Pagemaker, or maybe not. No, I forget.
But they they they had like video, you
know, they were the competitor to Adobe
and so Schiller has been on the other
side of that divide making the essential
tools for the Mac. That just helps add
to that same perspective though of
knowing
how much leverage those companies had
over Apple. And you know, the two things
that were scarring to Apple were the
near bankruptcy. And so it's made the
company institutionally incredibly
frugal. And it and more so while Jobs
was still alive. It was only after Jobs
died and Cook took over that they
started doing things like shareholder
buybacks and stuff. While Jobs was
alive, they were just hoarding their
profits. like they just were putting it
into that Brayburn Capital subsidiary
and just sitting on an ever growing
mountain of cash because in the same way
that like my grandparents who had been
through the Great Depression would like
eat scrape every single bit of food off
their plate and thought it was
offensive. No matter whether you thought
it tasted good or whether you were still
hungry, it was offensive not to eat
every bit of food offered to you because
they remembered not having enough food.
and the parts of the company that
remembered being on the verge of
bankruptcy in some ways it helps focus
the company but in some ways in the long
run sort of hurt them and I think having
somebody new like Tim Cook you know
again he's been there a long time but he
wasn't there for the near bankruptcy
part or came in just after and so he
wasn't as scarred by it but I think that
developer relations part definitely has
now that Apple has gotten big has hurt
them, right? That they're still so
thinking of themselves as underdogs who
want to assert not dominance over
developers from their perspective, but
having at least 51% of the power over
developers that they've lost the fact
that they've actually got like 95% of
the power or whatever, however you want
to assign the power dynamic in the
current state. They're so hellbent on
making sure they never fall below 51% of
the power between the platform and the
developers that they've just lost sight
of how overwhelmingly they've already
won and how much it would be in their
interest to to make concessions
because of the surplus of power that
they have to bolster developer goodwill.
I don't think we're putting them on a
hypothetical psychiatrist's couch, you
know, but they do remember it. It's
infused their thinking about the
company.
>> Yeah. And and we'll put a pin in that to
come back to as we talk about kind of
the more modern
era of lawsuits and regulation and
everything else like that. But stepping
back and walking through the history,
you do see a different Apple after that.
And so Apple does go on to build Keynote
and Pages and Numbers and the whole
digital hub and they start building more
and more of those key pieces of
software. I think in part from that
scarred time of, you know, we want to
make sure there's great software for the
average user and we're going to bundle
it even though that's in conflict with
our third party developers and we're
going to give things away free or cheap.
And you see a different Apple in the
that early 2000 era of like we're going
to control our destiny. Third party
developers are important. We're going to
be a platform. We're going to encourage
them, but we're we're going to cover our
own bases. We're going to make sure that
we're not beholden to these companies in
the long run by doing these things. And
then kind of the next era as as I was
going through all of this and this is
where I kind of like step into it is is
what I was calling the delicious era.
And there were these at the time, you
know, going all the way back to the 80s
kind of smaller passionate developers.
But I feel like the heyday of this like
passionate small developer time was
those early 2000s. You had Delicious
Monster building Delicious Library and
Panic and the Omni Group and Rogue
Amoeba and you could probably bare
bones. You could probably list another,
you know, 20 off the top of your head.
And there was this kind of renaissance.
The the iPod started driving more and
more people from Windows to the Mac.
There were these like really passionate
kind of fanboy developers building these
really cool software for the platform.
And as a platform, I feel like there was
a a bit of a heyday during that time
where Apple was kind of, you know,
Sherlocking famously came out of the the
Watson Sherlock thing in I think that
was 2002, but there was this this kind
of heyday leading up to the iPhone of
really great independent software
creators while at the same time, you
know, Microsoft and Adobe and others
we're starting to invest more back into
the platform and it it the Mac becomes
this really solid platform in that era.
It's a tough thing to strike a balance
on. It's almost impossible to just get
perfectly right where it's clearly
correct for there to be a suite of
fundamental apps out of the box in a
factory fresh new computer or phone or
tablet. and that therefore that 1990 to
1995 Apple mindset of we're not we're
hardly going to ship any firstparty apps
and everything will be third party apps
because we don't want to step on their
toes and even if we have a subsidiary
that makes Macrite and Macdraw and stuff
like that or FileMaker we're going to
put it in a subsidiary and try to treat
it as best we can as an actual
thirdparty developer even though we own
the company that's not the right way to
deal with a platform but obviously
Sherlocking every successful app is also
not the right mindset. You know, it's a
it's a hard balance to strike. And I
think they've managed it pretty well.
you know, especially and and again in
the early 2000s, like when sherlocking
first became a term, it was so few years
since the era when Apple studiously
avoided ever stepping on the toes of
third party developers that it felt like
all of this was newly offensive. And
here in 2025,
that's sort of ancient history. And so
people don't think of it that way. So,
for example, just this month at WWDC,
they announced Clipboard history
management in Sherlock on Mac OS Tahoe
and a sort of more
launch bar Alfred Raycast style
superpowers in Spotlight where you can
assign a two-letter abbreviation to
something to launch a shortcut or
something like that. I think that they
continue to strike the right balance
where I, as a longtime LaunchBar user,
I'm I'm glad they're adding those
features to Spotlight, but there's 0%
chance that I'm switching to Spotlight.
I have an example though where here's a
market where I feel like they tried to
stay away from third parties and I think
it bit them and now they're entering
late, which is password management,
right? And one password is a great app
from a great company that used to make a
really great Macass Mac app for
passwords and they're still a good
company and the app is still fine. I've
never been a user of it, but I see why
people are. But the dynamic is the more
popular and successful one password
came, the more that grew and they grew
in interest to want to reach the enter
quote unquote enterprise market. And
that changed the product in a way that
made it not so great as a Apple product,
you know, an Apple platform product. One
password is still a great product, super
good at a technical level, super useful
in that enterprise context and in terms
of some of the family sharing and stuff
like that. But it's like if you really
want the Mac style interface for
password integration and the iPhone
style integration and the syncing
between the two, it's started becoming
not as great as it used to be because
their interest in growing their market,
which is great for the company, were in
conflict with making it perfect for the
Apple platforms. And so Apple came out
with Apple Passwords, I think last year.
I think it's only been a year. Maybe
it's two years.
>> I don't know. It's been a well I mean
the the password app but they've they've
been kind of like slow rolling into
building the pass password app.
>> It was effectively an app worth more
than an app a serious app worth of
capabilities and features but hidden
away in a system settings panel
>> for years I think out of deference to we
don't want to squash this market. But
then I think as the market sort of moved
into a less and less idiomatic Apple
platform style of software, they were
like, you know what, we should just make
our own app because we could do this in
a way that's very Apple. And I think now
the new passwords app, it's a very very
it's a good introduction to like how do
you make a modern app for Apple
platforms. Any any area where they try
to stay out of eventually they find
themselves having to enter.
>> Yeah. So this is this is a huge can of
worms that we could spend an hour
talking about the balance of Apple, you
know, what they ship and what they don't
and what developers toes they step on
and what they don't. May maybe this is a
whole another podcast, but I wanted to
step back and see if there was anything
else you wanted to share relating to the
2000s in that I feel like that era did
actually set Apple up really well for
the iPhone as a platform that the the
Cocoa frameworks, the passionate
developer base, the books that were
written. You know, when I started
working on iOS, I I intended to be the
programmer and do it all myself. And so
I bought the famous book of the era,
Aaron Hildigas's Cocoa Frameworks or
whatever it was. And so by the time you
got to the iPhone, there was this really
solid, passionate community, books being
written, conferences being attended, WWC
had grown tremendously, and this era of
the 2000s of the Mac becoming this
really great platform was a springboard
that then propelled the iPhone even
faster as a platform than I think it
would have otherwise been. So, anything
else we wanted to talk about that era
before we jump into the iPhone era?
>> The basic mindset in the late 90s in the
industry was a sort of consensus that h
user interface design doesn't matter
that much. Nobody would argue it doesn't
matter at all. But that Apple's focus on
making it like the top priority of their
platforms wasn't worth it because okay,
let's just concede that the Mac was a
better user interface than Windows. Look
at their market share. So obviously it
didn't matter and it wasn't an
unreasonable conclusion but I think it
was wrongheaded because I think that the
problem that people arguing that way
didn't see yet was that no computer and
again it comes back to that argument
that the iPhone is truly the first real
personal computer. The one that
everybody every person would want and
would care about. And at the time in the
even in the late '9s, too many people
making decisions about what computers to
buy or what computers a company should
buy weren't the sort of people who care
that much about user interface. And
therefore, they were buying Windows PCs
based on other criteria.
And those early 2000s that built up this
skill set in designers and developers
and built up these teams of either
companies or independents or just
hobbyists but at every level who could
make software that was like, "Oh man,
just look at it." Right? Like remember
the disco app? It was a DVD burning
utility and when it burned a DVD, it
actually had smoke come out of the
window. Some people are like, "Well,
that's just a complete waste of CPU and
GPU resources." And other people are
like, "Where do I buy this, right? Like,
I want to buy this because when I burn a
CD or DVD, I want smoke to come out of
the window because that's just cool and
fun." And the this whole skill set was
there for Apple and and in 2008 when the
App Store opened up to build apps that
people would just be like, "But just
look at it, right? Just look at this.
Oh, yeah. Where do I get that app? I
want to get it. And it fueled this
consumer
fervor for the platform that no other
platform could even hope to compete with
at the time. There was no other
platform. Early Android, they just
couldn't do it. Microsoft's mobile,
Blackberry, whatever. Nobody had the
skill set. There was impossible to make
anything that was like, just look at it.
Just look at this app, right? And look
how cool it looks.
>> Yeah. I hadn't thought about it from
that the design perspective as well. And
and I mean that that's what brought me
to iPhone development and and we'll kind
of move into the iPhone era now is that
I was that uber passionate Apple fanboy,
Mac nerd. I had my I don't even know
what it was at the time in 2007, some
PowerBook that I had at the time. And I
loved the software. I loved the
platform. I was, you know, first person
in not first person in line. I was well
I was first person in line to buy an
iPhone but I was I was in line and again
like if if you weren't around and
weren't a fanboy at the time it's
laughable to think about this at the
time but I stood in line for I think it
was iOS t Mac o my iOS Mac OS Tiger or
one of those there would be lines at the
Apple store an OS update was a launch
event like
>> and you had to pay $129 $9 for it.
>> Yes, you would line up to pay $120 to
upgrade your operating system. But there
was it was that passion about the
platform at that time that you had
people like me and millions of us around
the country who cared so deeply about
the platform for all of these reasons is
that it wasn't just good hardware. It
wasn't just the OS, but it was this
combination of OS and fun software and
delightful, but it was productive. I I
specifically bought in 2003, I actually
bought that 17inch PowerBook because I
was using Photoshop to manipulate these
aerial photography for my dad's
commercial real estate business. And the
Windows laptop I was on kept crashing
and I was like, "Dad, I I I got to get a
Mac if you want me to keep working on
this stuff." You know, went and paid for
it. and the the experience was night and
day working on Photoshop on a 17-inch
PowerBook than it was whatever crappy
Windows machine I was using at the time.
And so there was this fervor for the
platform in that time that I think was
the perfect setup. And also coming into
the iPhone, there was enough of that
ground swell of people like me. You
know, I I was in China when Apple
announced the iPhone and I went to the
internet cafe at a Beijing hotel to
watch a live blog of the Mac World
keynote that you were at um when they
announced the original iPhone because
there was just that level of fervor. And
then, you know, 6 months later, my
brother and I go get in line to buy the
first iPhone. there was that that
passion and then by the time they
announced the SDK that next year I
jumped into it because I thought you
know this is going to be something I saw
something different about the platform
and so much of that had been built up
through Apple's experience across the
decades building platforms of the
turnaround of the Mac of building the
foundations with Coco and stuff like
that that ended up becoming the iPhone
and then by the time the iPhone app
store was released, there was this
ground swell of developers who were just
so excited about the platform. They
couldn't not build an app for this
platform. And it wasn't just original,
you know, Mac developers. And that was
one of the fascinating things, and you
kind of alluded to it earlier, is that a
lot of the Mac developers
didn't really do well on the iPhone
because they were kind of maybe a little
too caught up in what they had built for
the Mac. And what we saw happen when the
I app store launched with so many new
companies being built, new ideas being
explored and just this fervor for
building for the platform.
>> There was a skill set that transferred
immediately where somebody who is really
fluent as a developer in Objective C and
the the AppKit APIs on the Mac could
immediately jump over and because it was
just more limited. It was like appkit
but a lot more limited. But in terms of
the syntax and the style of the APIs,
they could just jump right in and thrive
in a way that a developer who was
familiar with Java at the time, which
was super popular, or the Windows C++
APIs was like, "What the hell's going on
here with all the square brackets?" But
in terms of the concepts for what an app
should be and do and the scope of it, it
wasn't a mini Mac, right? It really it
still isn't, but especially in 2008,
2009, it just was so much more limited
and the context of where and how people
would use it was so different that it
just sort of at a conceptual level be
thinking in a very different way. Not
quite as profound, but along the lines
of the difference between the purely
command line interfaces of the early PC
era where you just had text on a screen
versus a graphical user interface. It
was the same sort of difference where it
was like, hey, people are just going to
sometimes open your app and want to use
it like tap tap done and get out. You
could have Mac apps at the time where
you'd launch the app and it would show a
splash screen. you know, it was a whole
term of art like, you know, Photoshop
and and Adobe apps famously would take,
you know, 30 40 seconds to launch
because they were doing they were such
big apps. Well, that made no sense on
the iPhone, you know, and if you sort of
had that mindset like I have this idea
for an app, but it's going to take like
20 seconds to launch. Well, it's like
people would just be like, nah, screw
this. I'm going hitting the home button
and deleting the app before the before
it finish launching. to bring back the
kind of developer relations thread, WWDC
2008, which you were at. One of my big
regrets in life is not going to WWC 2008
because I founded my company April of
that year to to build iPhone apps. and I
had borrowed money from my family and I
felt this tension of am I spending my
family's hard-earned money that they've
invested in me to go on a vacation to
San Francisco to this developer
conference and so I did not go and what
I heard in retrospect was that they were
actually signing up developer accounts
in person at WWC that year could have
been there day one had had I gone but
this was the first time WWDC ever sold
out and and I've heard stories about
past WWE's
they would be giving away tickets they
would be you know begging developers to
come and at WWC 2008 was the first time
it sold out and then from then on like
that ground swell of developer and the
platform becoming so powerful they never
again had to ask developers to come it
was sold out every year after that
eventually having to go to a lottery and
then there's one more one more point I
wanted to make was that at WW WC 2008.
The slides from the presentations
had the email addresses of Apple
Evangelists on the slide because they're
like, "Hey, email us. We need more
feedback. We want to know what's going
on." Even as like successful as the Mac
platform had become, this was still like
pre iPhone Apple and pre the iPhone
platform becoming what it became was
such a different Apple. And then, you
know, funny story, because I had not
gotten a developer account, I sent an
email to like five of the people
>> on the slides
>> on the slides and John Genzy of all
people responded to the email, gave me a
phone call, and I I mean, to this day, I
remember he actually just retired from
Apple and I had a lovely chat with him a
couple weeks ago at WWDC
on on the side because, you know, he
he's no longer at WBC at Apple. Oh, he's
no longer at Apple, but I saw him at
WWDC.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Such an incredible
human. But evangelists would put their
email on the slides and like it it it's
just hard in 2025
and the how secretive, how closed, how
like we choose you, you don't choose us.
How hard it is to get the attention of
Apple for the average developer. That
was the era before the iPhone platform
became so big. And it was clearly a
surprise to Apple. The whole idea that
jobs had to be talked into opening up an
API. And you know, I think that's
overstated a little to some degree.
>> I was going to say like how much of that
was just him blustering.
Well, like the difference is between
should there be third party apps for
iPhone versus should the iPod support
Windows. Now Jobs wholeheartedly was
against supporting Windows. He really
was all 100% on board with the iPod as a
thing to help sell the Mac and that
making it a Macon peripheral was in
Apple's interest because it would
bolster the Mac and every other
executive from Schiller to whoever else
was like we're holding back the iPod as
a platform by not supporting Windows and
you know there's multiple books that
have written about it where he's like
all right fine go do it but don't bother
me I don't want to know about it you
know and then he called it you know the
the iTunes for Windows glass of ice
water in hell. He was happy once it came
out and he could see it and he could say
that he was happy, but he was really
against it. I don't think he was against
opening the iPhone. I just think he
thought someday. I I do think that maybe
it it happened a little faster than he
thought. I don't think he anticipated
announcing it in 2007. And in fact, at
2007's WWDC was when they announced
their quote unquote sweet solution for
third party developers, which was a sort
of very small JavaScript library where
you could make like some web apps that
kind of sort of looked like native
iPhone apps.
>> They wouldn't have announced that in
June on the cusp of the iPhone going on
sale if they really thought, hey, we're
going to have a native SDK a year, you
know, early next year. And you know, and
then it was like September, October
where they just made an announcement
like, "Sure, all right, fine. We heard
you. We're going to open an SDK. Give us
a couple months to get it together.
We'll get back to you when it's ready."
I kind of think he he thought it was
sort of like, "We'll get to it in a
couple of years." But I think it it
already was proving more popular and
more resonant than he thought. I think
Jobs and everybody at Apple knew this
iPhone was a hit. They knew it was a
thing. They weren't surprised that it
was in sensation when they announced it,
but it was even more resonant and more
of a hit and bled out to more normal
people. But like when the iPhone first
came out in 2007 in the right away, like
in the summer of 2007, I'd be at Whole
Foods and I'd have like a shopping list
in a web app and somebody randos would
just come up to me and be like, "Is that
an iPhone? Is that an iPhone?" All the
time. I don't think Apple was
anticipating that level of broad
consumer appeal and it sort of
accelerated that. The WWDC thing is a
perfect example. Like before the iPhone,
they had a whole extra track at WWDC
like they called it the IT track for IT
professionals who managed Mac
installations in corporate environments.
And it was because, you know, they had
room. I don't know, I'm just ballparking
like 3,000 developers, but then like
2,000 IT professionals and like a whole
different track of sessions where
instead of talking about APIs for making
Mac apps, it was sessions related to
the, you know, very serious, you know,
it was a reasonable topic for a
conference, but it was almost like two
conferences in one. One for developers
and one for IT professionals just
because they wanted to fill up Moscone
and they had room. And with the iPhone,
it was like, oh, we got to get rid of
that. There was this whole resentment
because the it was I think a very good
and successful and popular conference
for IT professionals. But when the
popularity of the iPhone happened, it
was like, oh, they got to go. And then
it became like even Mac developers felt
like, hey, this used to be all about the
Mac. And now it's like session after
session after session is just about the
iPhone. We've talked about a lot of
things that are ultimately almost a
fluke of history that that things played
out the way they did from, you know,
Bill Gates saving Apple and all those
things. I can't help but think and and I
I wish I could remember their names to
give them credit for it, but very soon
after the iPhone was released, the
developers jailbroke the iPhone and
started writing native apps for it.
Craig Hawkenberry is one name I will
call out. I wonder if that jailbreak
scene and seeing what developers were
building under insane constraints
because when you jailbroke, Apple hadn't
documented APIs and it wasn't a real
SDK. Developers were having to reverse
engineer, you know, methods they could
call and how things were working. And I
can't help but think that some of Job's
changing his mind so quickly was because
of how innovative and how passionate
that base was. And and I mean I I ended
up buying it when when I started my
company. I bought a second iPhone
because I was too nervous to jailbreak
my own iPhone. So I bought a second
iPhone, jailbroke it and installed all
these apps for me as like a way to study
what apps could do. It's like you could
study as a developer in 2008 before the
app store was launched and you had 500
apps to poke around to see what people
were doing. I jailbroke a phone
specifically to to understand what could
be done and what people were doing and
what was going on with the platform. So
I can't help but think that that
Hawinberry and Steve Shoutton Smith and
some of those other early Jailbreak
folks had an influence on the SDK
actually coming out as quickly as they
did. Yeah, I think Jobs appreciated
that. Lucas Newman, who was at Delicious
Library at the time and then went to
Apple. I think it got him hired by
Apple. I haven't heard from him in a
while. I also know that
>> I think this is a public story,
>> but Lucas Newman wrote the first game.
It was called Lights Off. wholly
backwards engineered entirely, you know,
and and Hawenberry came out with a
version of Twitter that was a native app
before the year was out without any SDK
from Apple, but building apps for the
iPhone through Xcode. It just bananas to
me that that this happened. But I think
Jobs appreciated that sort of mindset
because of all the crazy nonsense him
and W had done back in the day before
they they founded W, you know, before
they founded Apple, like making the
little blue boxes that would let you
make free long distance calls on a pay
phone and stuff.
>> Yeah. The enthusiasm was so much more
just so much stronger where it was like
they'd be crazy not to to hold it back,
you know. So then, you know, March uh
6th, 2008, a date seared into my memory,
they announced the iPhone SDK. And this
is again where I think people in 2025
don't appreciate
what a different era that was in terms
of
what was possible as a developer to
build a business. And I I wrote a
business investment thesis that I sent
to my my dad and mom and aunt and uncle
who ultimately invested in the company.
And I specifically wrote in there like
what an incredible deal this is that I
don't have to host my own like store
because back then I mean and it's so
easy to forget in this era of Stripe and
AWS backends and everything like that
that standing up your own web server to
distribute apps especially if it's a
larger app could get very expensive.
Bandwidth was expensive. working with
third-party payment platforms was a
hassle expense. You had needed a whole
team to like sort all that kind of stuff
out. And so when Apple announced the
iPhone
>> and especially on a phone, right, like a
credit card would be even harder.
There's no way to scan it, no tap to
pay.
>> The only software that was on phones at
the time was carrier build and you had
to do a deal with a carrier and they
took 50% of everything. The app store
was genuinely
a revolution in in software of a
revolution of opportunity for
developers. And I mean this is what I
built my career on. And this is why I
have such a soft place in my heart and
am so obsessed to this day with the app
store because it it just fundamentally
changed the opportunity you had as a
developer to build a business. And of
course, that's not true anymore in 2025
with Stripe and hosted backends and
bandwidth being essentially free and all
these thirdparty SAS tools that you
could spin up a web app. And I mean,
gez, now even in vibe coding where, you
know, you don't even need a backend or
hardly any experience to like spin up a
web app that's just hosted on Replet and
you can charge for it via like built-in
payment solutions. And it's just crazy
how much different the world is today
than it was for that original App Store
release. And I think people today forget
just how powerful that was. And you
know, we we're talking about this before
we hit record, trying to do the math,
but there are there are kids today,
teenagers, releasing apps on the App
Store, whose parents probably weren't
even alive when Schiller and Q and
Jazwak joined Apple in the 80s. You
could be a 16-year-old developer with a
40-year-old parent who wasn't even alive
when all of this started with the
Macintosh in 1984, much less 1976 when
Apple was founded. And I think there is
just a little bit of a loss of history
and then maybe at Apple a little too
much recognition of history of here we
are in 2025 and the world is completely
changed and the iPhone helped change the
world 17 years ago but now it's been 17
years since the world changed and people
today looking from the outside without
this history I don't think appreciate
the things that Apple appreciates like
they don't have the context and the
history and I think when you're trying
to understand how Apple operates why
they're you know so insistent on the app
store fees and other things like that
you have to kind of ignore all of that
history which to people's credit they
don't even know and that's why we're
doing this podcast but it's like to
understand Apple you have to go back
those 40 years and and see all of what
it took to get to the iPhone and then
the iPhone becoming the platform it is
and the billions and trillions of
dollars that the platform has generated
for third party developers that's hard
not to just appreciate to some extent at
this point it's becoming clear that
Apple itself has sort of fallen into the
same trap and I'll exemplify it with a
quote I've been thinking about this a
lot and I'm hopefully going to soon turn
it into some kind of article on daring
fireball but um there's a Steve Jobs
quote and it's actually Apple's made a
big plaque of it huge. It's like I don't
know 10 ft diagonal and it hangs not at
Apple Park but outside the town hall
theater at the old infinite loop campus.
And the quote is if you do something and
it turns out pretty good then you should
go do something else wonderful not dwell
on it for too long. Just figure out
what's next.
And I think with the app store in
particular, boy, does that really
resonate. And it's not that they should
forego all profit, you know, and all
commissions from the app store. The
whole, well, we started with 7030, we
should stick with 7030. We've never
raised it from 7030, even when it's
become more powerful or more monopoly or
whatever you want to call it, you know.
>> Yeah. as as they've increased in control
and the platform has increased in
importance, they could have increased
and squeezed and other things,
>> right? and the people at Apple who are
insisting on keeping as much of the
commissions and the rules and everything
as they have, but especially when it
comes to payments and letting people
link out to the web and and stuff like
that, that they're thinking, "Hey, we
built this thing that was so much more
generous and developer friendly than
everything that came before it on
handhelds or especially on phones that
they're still caught up in thinking of
what it was in 2008 as opposed to that
jobs quote. If you build something and
it turns out pretty good, then you
should go do something else wonderful,
not dwell on it for too long. I feel
like Apple is dwelling on the success
and the innovation, true innovation,
profound innovation that absolutely
shook up and completely
revolutionized the phone industry more
than Apple even revolutionized the PC
industry. but they're dwelling on it for
too long and that they should move on
and build something else new and sort of
start conceding on that issue. And I
think it is something that they've lost
with when they lost Steve Jobs. People
think that they lost the ability to make
new things, that it was always his
ability to drive them to make a new
thing. But I think he was good at like,
okay, fine. And again, I I mentioned
that whole iPod for Windows thing where
he stuck with it for a year or two and
then he was like, "Okay, fine, fine."
You know, at some point the people
holding on to all of these rules and
appealing all these decisions about the
anti- steering and stuff, somebody at
the top named Tim Cook should probably
just say, "Okay, fine. Fine. Let's just
give in on a lot of this and just we
don't have to worry about it anymore.
Just just clear clear it off our
concerns." And I think it would be so
good for Apple to just clear it off the
table and just clear their time and
their energy and their talent from
executives down to engineers to just
figure out what's next and make
something new that would build into
something where they have to worry about
this again in 10 or 15 years.
>> So I I want to dig into what I will
affectionately call app store 3.0
because I completely agree. But let's
step back one more point in history. And
I have a bunch of notes. We could go
through all of the the early iPhone
days. And you know, it's hard for people
to even remember you who don't even know
that there weren't inapp purchases that
you had paid upgrades that that in order
to do a paid upgrade, you had to release
a whole new app and then transition
users to it. Like there's so many points
on the App Store history of just
oddities and like stubbornness and and
weird things that Apple did in those
early days even as the platform started
taking off. But in 2016,
Phil Schiller did a round of interviews
and I I think the one that most you know
kind of concisely covers it and maybe
the one he gave the most access to was
Verge and they titled the article App
Store 2.0. And so in hindsight now, I
will give this way more credit than I
think I did at the time of it really was
App Store 2.0 and it really did fuel
what we see as kind of the current era
of the platform. They open up
subscriptions to all apps, which
obviously working at RevenueCat and now
all my apps are subscription. You know,
I know some users still still bulk at
it, but from a developer perspective and
being able to fund the creation of great
software and continue working on it,
like that was Revolution. That was App
Store 2.0 to empower developers to
better monetize apps. They sped up app
review significantly. Again, if if you
weren't around a decade ago, you don't
remember the days when it was 7 days, 14
days to get an app through app review.
So, as much as you might complain about
app review today,
at least you get that rejection in 24
hours to 48 hours instead of, you know,
7 to 14 business days. They dropped the
commission to 15% on year 1 renewal. So,
if you started a subscription, that
first commission would be 30 and then
after that would be 15%. They announced
app store search ads as a new way to pay
to to get users. You know, as much as we
can complain about, you know, name
squatting and having to pay to defend
your brand, it's an incredible
opportunity to be able to pay and get in
front of people right there in the app
store. And it and it it's actually the
paid acquisition channel that I
recommend any app start with. Like if
you're struggling to get downloads, the
first thing you should do is start
figuring out App Store ads. That was App
Store 2.0. and they started removing a
lot of these old apps that weren't
working or just crappy apps. They
started to kind of purge the App Store
and curate it a little bit more. And
that was App Store 2.0 in 2016. And
looking back now almost a decade since.
It really was a profound shift in the
app store that has led to
so much of what we now get to experience
as the app store would not have happened
had they not loosened the reigns in
those ways and made those changes. And
so, you know, as much as we talk about
and I complain on Twitter about Apple
being obstinate and, you know, not
changing and being stuck in the past and
everything like that, this was the App
Store 2.0 know was them changing, you
know, did they go on an apology tour?
Did they whatever? No. But they made
like very fundamental changes to the app
store that propelled it for this last
decade. But and to your point, and this
is what I want to get back to today in
2025, is that it really does feel like
we're in need of App Store 3.0, a
deeper, more fundamental rethink of the
opportunity. And I think to your point,
get out of the way. Let developers
build. I I think the vision pro is a
good example too of the animosity that
has kind of started to build up, the
frustrations and everything has gotten
to a point where developers are way more
weary of Apple. And you you posted some
really great posts this spring, Apple,
you're killing my vibe. And then another
one by John Syracusa just about
developers seeing Apple more and more as
a inconvenience to reaching their users
versus a partner in building this
incredible platform and the iPhone
continues to sell like hotcakes. Apps
are making money handover fist.
Developers are building apps, new apps
every day. So from the outside and
looking at the numbers, maybe the
platform is fine. But I think this
sentiment, this kind of where developer
relations are in 2025 with the lawsuits,
with the DMA, with all of the things
that are going on, it feels like we're
due another kind of reset. Personally, I
would love I would love to that be a
little bit more like the 97 jobs of
like, hey, we did some things that we
thought were right at the time and the
forthrightness to say, here's why we
think this. Here's why we did it. We're
changing our mind and we're going to
focus on building these great platforms
moving forward. And you know what does
Apple need for the next decade and the
decade after
a vibrant developer community who's
going to jump on the next AR platform?
You know, Meta and Google and OpenAI and
others are chomping at the bit and have
billions of dollars to invest to not let
this next platform play out the way the
smartphone platform played out with
Apple having so much control and so much
power. Maybe it's time for a bigger
change.
>> It's just proven so lucrative and you
know forms the backbone of their
services quote unquote services that
they report financially which has been
their growth vector for the last I don't
know seven or eight years. Not because
interest in the iPhone has decreased,
but because clearly the iPhone is
literally so popular that every single
person in the world who lives somewhere
where the iPhone is available and they
can afford one and they want one has
one. It's that popular that it has
peaked because they've run out of people
to sell it to. And to their credit, you
know, and it's part of the appeal that
they build them to last, you know,
that's good for the environment. as good
as just a message, you know, that
they're durable and that silicon is so
good that five, sixyear-old iPhones are
still very credible devices. I'm running
iOS 26 on an iPad from 2018, iPad Pro.
It is a little slow, but you know,
that's a seven-year-old device. The
services, quote unquote, services has
been their growth for the last seven or
eight years. And a lot of that comes
not, you know, they would like you to
think that it's from Apple services,
from people paying for iCloud and paying
for Apple TV Plus and whatever else they
sell as a as a service, but a lot of it
comes from their commission from the app
store. But they could decrease their cut
and they could open up and just instead
of fighting for these anti- steering
things, especially the going to the web
stuff, which I've been against for years
and years. I mean pretty much ever since
it became an issue that this is
ridiculous that you know especially like
in the Kindle exemplifies it that if the
terms of the app store are such that the
Kindle app cannot sell app or books in
the app without losing money on each
book which is the way the ebook
publishing industry works where there's
like a 7030 split between the book
seller and the publisher and therefore
if there's a 7030 split between the
publisher and the platform they they
literally lose money on each sale that
they'd owe a $10 book, they would owe $3
to Apple, but they would owe $7 to the
publisher. And therefore, you know, at
best would make nothing. So, why do it?
If you can't sell books through the app
because of the terms of your store, you
should absolutely let them have a button
that says go here to go buy books on the
Kindle website. And the idea that they
fought that is it's just absurd and
clearly anti-user. And it just
exemplifies how they've gotten caught up
in thinking way too much that the point
of the app store is for Apple to get a
commission on all software digital
content sales for the platform as
opposed to what it should be and could
be and should remain going forward which
is us maintaining control and having
approval over the software and the APIs
and what can happen in the background
and how things are managed. and how
privacy is managed and the sandbox and
everything is the best for the platform
long-term and very much the best
interest of the users. It should be that
thinking and then the fact that we make
a lot of money but maybe not as much
money for all digital content on the
platform because we do have and one of
the ways you can do inapp purchases
should be icing on the cake which is
clearly how they thought of it at the
outset and they should just go back to
thinking that and I really do think that
if and when they do and I think it's a
big if but you know and and not at the
point of regulation because if it's at
the point of regulation. We see it.
They're just going to make it convoluted
and complex. And the only way this is
really going to get this knot is going
to get untied is for Apple to willingly
say, you know what, we're going to like
lower the rate to 8020 for everyone and
9010 for small business or something
like that. And we're going to just drop
if you want to send people outside the
app to the web to make their purchases,
just give them a button and they'll go
to the web to to do it. If they did
that, I honestly think they they would
not see a significant decrease. And I
think we're going to see that proved out
in the coming months and quarters as
Apple releases their quarterly finance
statements after the recent ruling here
in the US, their biggest market that
allows stuff like that. I don't think
we're going to see a decrease in
services revenue, you know, now that
they've been forced to open this up. So
why not just open it up worldwide and
make it easier for everyone and stop
hanging this sort of democlesese over
everybody that hey if we win an appeal
in a year or two we're going to revoke
this access that you've now gotten at
the point of Judge Ivon Gonzalez Rogers
legal declaration it's better for the
platform just make people happy make
developers happy and users happy and
Apple will profit from it they really
will
>> it does seem like dropping
the fee would be a huge huge change in
developer relations in developer sent
sentiment. I I would hope they would go
all the way down to 8515
and I think there's, you know, Ben
Thompson
>> and maybe something different for games.
Maybe.
>> Yeah, that's what I was going to say.
Yeah, maybe games stay at 80 at 7030
because that's what Sony and Nintendo
and Steam and everybody else charges
except for Epic
with their app store, but they obviously
have uh reasons to artificially, you
know, put that lower. But I can't help
but think it would change the tone with
the industry more broadly and be more in
line with the reality of 2025. Now, you
can argue, well, you're not just paying
for payment fees. I think that's a
disingenuous argument that a lot of
people make. It's like, oh, you know,
Stripe is 3%, you know, why should we be
paying Apple 30% for for payments? Well,
you're not paying Apple 30% for
payments. And and this is the argument,
you know, Apple continues to make is
that it's a platform fee, but there's a
couple of things in there. One, it's
almost a fluke of history that
Jobs in that original iPhone
announcement said, "Hey, if you have a
free app, we're going to distribute it
for free and doesn't cost you anything."
And at the time, that was great. And
that created companies like Facebook and
Uber and others where they might not
have been able to make it work. Well,
Facebook's a bad example because they
were already, you know, reasonably
profitable, but the iPhone certainly
did, you know, springboard them even
further.
>> Yeah. But I I I would argue that the the
company is it's not just that they
adjusted and adapted to mobile. Meta
today is unrecognizable from the
Facebook of 2007. And in hindsight, they
were clearly meant for mobile. And to
the point where they've got products
that people use entirely on mobile,
right? You can technically use Instagram
on the web, but the vast majority of
Instagram users have never once used it
on the web.
>> But would Instagram exist as it is today
if they had had to pay 50 cents per
download or they had to pay, you know,
per user?
>> It is a quirk, you know, that Apple
because Apple was coming at it from the
mindset of the way the Mac worked that
there were free apps, but that any
company that wanted to run the business
from the app would be selling copies of
the app. You'd buy the app before you
installed it. And that was Apple's
mindset. And again, they were selling
copies of their operating system at the
time. If you bought a Mac that had Mac
OS 10.2 installed and wanted to upgrade
to 10.3, it cost $129. And it cost
hundred some dollars or I don't even
know what it cost to get pages and
numbers in uh Keynote. You know, all of
that stuff was for sale for what would
today strike people as bananas amounts
of money. And that was their thinking of
how software would be sold. And I think
the idea of a company and Meta
exemplifies it that a company you know
like one of the five biggest companies
in the world purely making software well
I mean I know they've got those glasses
and stuff now too but for you know like
Microsoft primarily a software company
would be making all their money by
giving apps away and only having ads in
the app. It just didn't compute at the
time and they never foresaw that. It's a
sort of a loophole. And if it cost them
50 cents a download per user per year,
they could afford that very easily. They
could, but then would Instagram have
been created like could so many
companies who have been built on top of
it, you know, could they have done it?
But in 2025, when you look at the state
of the world of Airbnb making billions
of dollars, Uber making billions of
dollars, Meta making billions of
dollars, Google making billions of
dollars on the iOS platform and not
having to pay a penny other than a $100
a year developer account, and here I am,
indie developers, supporting my family.
I've paid Apple over a million dollars,
I think, closing in on $2 million in my
17-year history. Is that fair? And in
the world of 2025, that just seems
bananas. Like, why have I paid Apple $2
million for my dinky little indie apps
and Meta has paid Apple $100 a year for
17 years? It's bizarre. When you if you
erase 40 years of history, if you erase
all the context that we've like built up
to this point and you just look at it as
a logical person in 2025, that just
seems bananas that I am paying so much
to Apple and Metas paying zero.
>> I do think that was some of the thinking
behind the core technology fee for the
EU DMA compliance plan where it was sort
of like what would we do if we did it
all over again? And I think that 50
cents per user per year fee for, you
know, million plus download apps only
was sort of thinking this is what they
would do all over again. But at the
irony of that is that they're even
walking away from that now because the
EU has said that the CTF is not
compliant with the DMA. So they're
switching to a core technology fee or or
commission which again is only on inapp
purchases, you know. So again, if you
have a super popular app like Instagram
that you can use without ever making a
digital goods transaction through it,
Apple makes nothing but the $100 a year
developer fee. I do think they're
thinking of it and they tried. You know,
the CTF was sort of their attempt, but
it is sort of a tricky position, but I
think the answer to that is, hey, maybe
they you should just be happy that you
own this platform and not worry about
how much money you make from it. And
again like that Steve Jobs quote and
just make something else wonderful and
go on and really refocus on getting
developers to say if I didn't have to
answer to my boss or what I'm telling my
boss and manager I think we should do is
put our efforts into making awesome
software for these Apple platforms to
get that developer enthusiasm back I
think is worth more to the company than
whatever money they're making by
breeding pure resentment with the
current policy. And yeah, I don't want
to let it slide because you you
mentioned it, but I want to emphasize it
that one of those differences between
Vision OS today and the original Mac in
1984 1985
at this point based on where we are in
Vision OS's life is that even though the
Mac wasn't popular in 1985, there was
this blossoming
ecosystem of native Mac software. even
though the the market share wasn't there
because of the enthusiasm developers had
who were like oh my god people it just
clicked in their heads like this is the
computer of the future I want to make
software for it and you're we're not
seeing that for the for vision we really
aren't there are cool apps and it's not
a dead platform but it's nowhere near
vision OS today is nowhere near as
vibrant a third party developer
ecosystem as the Mac was in 1985 or 1986
six. And I think that should be the red
flag for Apple. And I think there might
be a little surprised by that. I don't
think they're surprised by the number of
Vision Pro headsets they've sold, but I
think they are a little disappointed and
surprised by the lack of developer
enthusiasm for the platform. And I think
it's entirely because developers are so
resentful of the way that Apple has
treated them, specifically around
finance and and payments, that sort of
thing. you know the we can argue about
the rules on background processing and
stuff like that in in sandboxing and
stuff that apps would like to do but
it's really the resentment first and
foremost numbers 1 2 and three on the
list of reasons why developer relations
are strained with Apple has to do with
money anybody who says otherwise is is
wrong and Apple doesn't need money again
they are not operating on narrow profit
margins their profit margins have gone
up not down this is The tricky point
though, and this is uh this is me
listening to too much Ben Thompson, but
the tricky thing for Apple at this stage
though is that the is that the services
revenue is so important to the growth
narrative around the stock that even
though they don't need the money, they
need the money to continue growing the
stock at the pace it's growing. And
that's the like rock and a hard place
that they've gotten themselves into is
that the services narrative is so strong
and that quarter over-arter growth in
services revenue and services profit
when the hardware has kind of started to
flatline a little bit. I don't want to
interrupt you, but it's like the the
Exxon Mobile of the world ran into this
problem when they were on top of this
market cap lists, you know, where it's
like, well, how much more how many more
cars and motorcycles and airplanes
consuming fossil fuels could we have,
right? It's like everybody who could
have one had one, you know, and they're
not going to make cars that purposefully
consume more fuel. There comes a point
where a product or a service or a
category really does max out in terms of
human population and it's a good place
to be. But if your mindset as a Wall
Street investor is growth, growth,
growth, how much more could they grow,
right?
>> Yeah. And maybe this is where we need to
go back to the Steve quote from 1997.
And maybe the message is as much to Wall
Street as it is to developers and Apple
saying to Wall Street, we're going to
need to take some lumps potentially,
like you and I have said. I mean, if
they drop the fee to 15%, would they
lose money? Maybe. But maybe net maybe
Netflix would come back to the app
store. Maybe, you know, in my job at
Revenue Cat, I talked to so many
developers who are just web web. You
know, we're trying to push as much as we
can to the web. we're going to
experiment with pushing out of the app
into the web now because it's more
profitable. You know, we want to save on
that 30%. And so if they drop the fee
and it just didn't even make sense to
charge on the web because at revenue
cap, we did some experiments and Netflix
did some experiments with Apple early in
the Epic case. I think it came out that
their number was somewhere around that
like 12 to 13% where if the fee had been
dropped that low, it would still be more
profitable to operate in the app store
than outside the app store. And then
there's a lot of complicating factors
now too of like owning the relationship
and would Netflix want Apple to be an
intermediary. Well, guess what? If Apple
were a more friendly intermediary, maybe
they wouldn't mind so much and they
would just pick the one that was more
profitable on the dollar for-doll basis.
We know it's a solvable problem because
there are more platforms for signing up
customers that give the owner of the
service, the newsletter, the streaming
service, the music service, whatever it
is, more direct relationship with their
customers. We know, we've seen them
built. So, Apple could obviously build
one into the app store. You know,
instead of making all these entitlements
over linkouts and stuff like that, make
it an entitlement where you kind of have
to qualify and have these restrictions
on, well, do you have a customer service
department? What's your refund policy?
We're going to enforce that you have a
customer-friendly refund policy where
you don't have to call a 1-800 number
and listen to somebody try to talk you
out of unsubscribing. We're going to
test it. You know, that's part of app
review where it has to be as easy to
unsubscribe as to subscribe. Otherwise,
we will pull your entitlement, you know,
and but then if you, you know, qualify
on those terms and you have those
policies in place, you can have more of
a direct relationship with your
customers. Do whatever it takes to make
developers happy to be building for the
Apple platforms. Instead, they're
they're focusing they're clearly
focusing on how can we extract a decent
enough portion of the revenue that's
conducted on these platforms. And so
taking liberties with the Steve Jobs
quote from 97, Apple's going to need to
take some lumps in the coming months,
but we're going to take it like an
adult. And I'm proud of that. And the
result of that focus, focusing more on
developers and building a fantastic
platform over extracting as much revenue
as we can from that platform. We and
thirdparty developers are going to build
some really great products where the
total is much greater than the sum of
the parts. I post on Twitter about
Apple all the time and like I know a lot
of people inside Apple don't like me for
for some of those posts but what I care
about deeply is this app store platform.
>> Join the club you recently. It's that
you and I care unreasonably about the
this platform. On an earlier podcast
with Ben Thompson, I love this quote
from him. He said, "It just breaks my
teenage heart to see Apple continuing
the down this path that it's going on."
And I think that you and I both have
gotten to this level of frustration with
developer relations and what Apple's
doing and the way they're operating. Not
because we hate Apple and want to see
them fail and and not because we're like
just take joy in, you know, ridiculing
them or complaining and criticizing them
publicly. It's just that we care so
deeply and we see the path that they're
on and we don't think it's right. And if
you take these 40 years of history, you
can kind of justify things and you can
see how internally they they can justify
it and see it this way and see it that
way. Somehow they've gotten attached to
this income that they've extracted from
commissions in the app store in a way
that they've never been attached to
other things. And you and I mentioned
this during this podcast about the
upgrade charge they used to charge for
operating systems. $129 to go from Mac
OS 10.3 to 10.4. They used to charge $5
to upgrade iOS. They clearly at that
time were trying to get away from it,
but they thought the accounting rules
they were trying to follow required them
to do it. But and they just don't
they've given up on that knowing that it
was better for them overall. In theory,
you think, well, why would you ever if
people were doing it and lining up
outside Apple stores to buy boxed
versions of the software for $129 to
upgrade their existing Mac? Why would
you ever do away with that if it was so
popular that they were lining up? But in
the grand scheme of things, it's clearly
was the right decision to just make the
operating system upgrades free, to
encourage all users to upgrade and to
sort of steer them towards automatic
updates because they can do that because
they're not charging, right? They
couldn't do the automatic OS updates
that most people with their default
settings on a Mac or iPad or iPhone
just, you know, at some point a couple
months after the O release, there's a
version they think is stable enough and
overnight while your phone's charging,
you get the new oper, you know, you're
going to have iOS 26 in November,
December this year. And they can only do
that because they're not charging for
it. And it's better for them overall.
They're obviously they've never made
more money. Their profits and revenue
are at record highs. I think the same
thing is true of the commissions in the
app store that yes at some level if
you're the CFO at Apple you're like well
why in the world would we ever decrease
this if we don't legally have to why
would we ever give up a penny of it it's
a lot of money but it'll all work out in
the end in terms of and Jaws himself has
mentioned this in multiple of the
interviews he did do last month at WWDC
he said the same thing to me and it's an
it was an off thereord briefing I had
with him and it was very cordial and
nice. I'm sure he won't mind me
repeating it cuz he mentioned it on the
record with Joanna Stern and multiple
people where one of the things Steve
Jobs often said, "If we make great
products and tell people about them,
that's the marketing part from his
perspective. Tell them why they're
great, it'll all work out in the end."
That's just as true of the app store as
anything else. But it's this one area
where they've just got like a compulsive
institutional obsession with with
squeezing it that they do not need.
>> And speaking of of flukes of history,
one of the I think it was an Epic case
found an email from Schiller to Jobs
saying, "What if what if we cap app
store revenue to Apple at $100 million?"
Which at the time seemed
>> I think it was a billion. I think it was
a billion. Okay.
>> I think it was a billion.
>> Even a billion. It's like at the point
in time when he wrote that, it probably
sounded crazy. Like how will we ever
make that much money on the app store,
but then now, you know, in hindsight,
it's like, oh my gosh, that said such a
tiny amount to what they're making now.
But had Jobs been convinced of that, and
had they announced publicly, we're going
to cap Apple's revenue on the App Store,
>> or even if they never announced it
publicly,
>> it became internal policy.
>> Yeah. And that once it hit a billion,
they drop it to 7525 and it stayed at a
billion and it was growing some more and
then they could drop it to 8020, you
know, and then eventually 8515, you
know, who knows? By now they'd probably
be at 9010 or 90 937 or something like
that. And at certain level then without
ever having announced that they could
stop, right? Like if it had ever gotten
even to 9010, they could stop and say,
"Well, now we can just sort of let it
grow because 10 is pretty fair, right?"
And yes, it's not the 2.7% Stripe takes
or whatever, but 7% is, you know,
arguably pretty good deal for everything
the App Store offers.
>> And imagine how different the last
decade of developer relations would have
been had Apple capped it at that. And
then the incentive wasn't for the
financial side of things. The incentive
was to build a fantastic platform for
developers and empower them to serve our
customers and keep innovating and
encourage developers and designers and
even the companies and managers at those
who aren't nerds and and are into the
platform, but just to encourage as much
as they can the mindset of maybe we
should build this for Apple platforms
exclusively because of the great APIs
and capabilities, you know, and why even
bother with these other platforms? we
don't make any money on them. We're
doing so great iOS only. Like they've
really gotten away from that. It's it's
to Apple's benefit in obvious ways to
have as many developers as possible
making Apple platform exclusive
software. And at this point there's such
a resentment that there's so many people
whether they're managers or executives
or developers or just users who are
like, "Well, you'd be crazy to build for
Apple only because they're sort of
against you in terms of trying to take
your money." As a long-term
Apple watcher and being friends with so
many developers, what do you think it
would take? Is a reset even in the cards
for Apple at this point? Like would it
take Phil Schiller on stage at the
iPhone 18 or whatever? They don't do
anything on stage.
>> Well, right. But I mean, what would it
take to to get a reset above the I mean,
the money would would probably go a long
way like, okay, we're just going to drop
the rate, but it it does almost feel
like
>> there needs to be some level of that
1997 jobs humility of like, hey, we made
some mistakes. You're going to see a new
Apple moving forward.
>> Yeah. But I think you don't have to do I
don't think it's within Apple to say we
made some mistakes and we're going to
change. even though that's sort of how
he addressed because he was willing to
say that at WWDC 1997 because what they
were scrapping were things that weren't
under him, right? Open do and Newton and
everything else they scrapped, they
weren't jobsled postn next reunification
projects. The Apple way of doing it
would be to act like we've come up with
this amazing new idea that only Apple
could do and it's totally innovative and
nobody else has ever suggested it before
and it was it's called taking less money
from the app store, right? and not
apologizing and not saying, you know,
presenting it as a new a new
opportunity, you know, in the same way
that they're pitching the liquid glass
of iOS 26 as, hey, the capabilities of
the hardware and the GPU and the screen
display technology with HDR is such that
we're able to present this interface
that we couldn't have done before. just
presented as the market opportunities
and the success of the iPhone are such
that we're able to have a new financial
set of rules around the app store that
we couldn't have done before even though
they could have you know but just say
that they couldn't you know it's just
frustrating on a human level it's like
at work when I do something stupid or
whatever you apologize like there
there's just humanity in that level of
humility that it it is just frustrating
to me on a human level but that would
count as an apology, right? It would cuz
we'd know
>> it would count for for us as like Apple
followers. It would. But I think in
2025, the press would have a field day
with that and just call BS in a way that
I don't know that it would work. And
this is kind of, you know, something
I've been thinking more and more is that
Apple needs to do some things unapplike
to adjust to the realities of 2025 and
to set themselves up for the next decade
as a platform for developers, as a
consumer brand, and everything else. For
example, the small business program was
so freaking Applelike. instead of just
saying hey 15% for the first million 30%
for everything after there was all these
rules like you got to get into the
program and then you get kicked out of
the program and it created all these
weird in like to me that's just the the
perfect example of how Apple overd does
things and so to usher in an app store
3.0 Oh, I think we need to see them do
things unapplike. And I think that
again, it's it's the fanboy in me just
wanting to see a new version of Apple.
Not that I hate Apple, not that I think
they're idiots inside Apple. Not that I
think anything poor of them as a
company. I want to see them succeed. I
like I want to wear Apple glasses, not
Meta Glasses, with a camera on them. And
I I think there's there's aspects of
like what they're building and the trust
they've built with consumers and
everything else that is setting them up
for potentially being that next human
computing platform. But having
developers on your side and enthusiastic
about it is going to be a huge huge huge
boon. And given how competitive Meta and
Google and OpenAI and others are and
will be in the coming years, maybe it
does require a bit deeper of a reset and
doing some things that aren't
traditionally how Apple operates. I
think even this WWDC was a little bit of
a reckoning in that Ben Thompson got it,
you got it, some people got it. Like,
hey, this is Apple,
you know, not overpromising. so that
they can overd deliver. But the press
had a field day with like, oh, it's a
boring, they're so far behind on AI and
like all that kind of stuff. Nobody
remembers that though. I mean, it's news
for a week and here we are a month out
and I think it's already forgotten, you
know, and I think Apple should have the
fortitude and the wisdom and you
mentioned at the outset that, you know,
their leadership's been there for so
long. They remember this. They know how
it goes and they should just be
confident in themselves in that way. The
other thing about the fact that so many
of the senior leaders have been there
for so long, it means that most of them
are nearing retirement. Schiller has
stepped down and is in a different
position as an Apple fellow. He still
runs events. He still runs the app
store. Tim Cook is I forget how many
what year is 64 or something like that
or 63. You know, Eddie Q and Jaws are in
their 60s. And I'm not saying any of
them are leaving soon. I mean, I'm sure
none of them are going to pre-announce
their retirements, but in terms of
setting things up for the next
generation of senior leadership at
Apple, which is coming sooner rather
than later, right? It's coming over the
next decade across the board. I think
that they need to reset the
institutional priorities of the company
because the new generation won't have
that experience from the '9s that you
brought up on this show to explain this.
And instead I if they took over right
now we just have the mindset of oh the
way Apple works is they expect 30% of
all the money on the platform. That's
just the way it is. and that they don't
have any history behind it or why, but
that they think that as opposed to
thinking that the most important thing
Apple should do is encourage, stoke and
keep going in an ongoing relationship
developer enthusiasm for building
exclusive software for our platforms,
you know, and making it as great as
possible and thinking some of the best
software experiences on our platforms
are going to come from our third party
develop velopers not from Apple and that
that's the way it should be and we
shouldn't be thinking that the all of
the best software comes from Apple and
it's you know an afterthought what third
parties make
>> and to your point I hadn't thought of
this until you you brought it up that in
setting things up for the future I think
there is onus on the current executives
to not hold on to the past for the next
decade when it's then too late they're
in the position today and having been at
Apple 40 years. But you know, one of the
impressive things about Meta these past
decade is that as a founder company,
Zuckerberg put a hundred billion dollars
into Reality Labs and is like force of
will and telling shareholders, hey,
we're making these massive investments
and they're going to pay off. And now
he's doing the same with AI, you know,
hund00 million checks to lure AI talent.
you know, that's not something the the
stock market normally would reward, but
he is out there pitching the world that,
hey, this is an investment worth making
and we're going to make it. And I think
these Apple executives who've been there
40 years are the best people to say and
convince the world, hey, we need to make
some investments on the developer front.
And that's going to involve less
services, revenue, or whatever it has to
be, but it's going to pay off in spades
in the long run with the innovation
that's going to happen with the renewed
developer sentiment and everything else
that they're going to need for this next
big platform in the coming 5 to 10
years. And it may be too late if they
hold on.
>> Oh, I agree. Well, I think that's a
fantastic place to wrap it up and and
really what I wanted to say on this
podcast and hopefully people have gotten
that depth of history of when you're
frustrated with Apple about this policy
or that there's a lot more going on
behind the scenes than and I mean even
again as much as I complain on Twitter
I'll acknowledge that I lack a ton of
context and I lack a lot of insight and
I'm sure I can understand why People
inside Apple are frustrated at the way I
frame things sometimes, but when you
take all of that history and everything
else into account, something needs to
change. I'm not sure exactly what that
is. And me lobbying is me just throwing
out ideas. Happy to be wrong about any
of this, anything I'm suggesting, but I
hope it's helpful to folks to better
understand Apple in these ways. If
there's one other point that I'll close
with, it would be that I mentioned
earlier that the problem Apple found
itself in in the early 90s when Jobs was
exiled was this. They were caught in
this 80s mindset of every couple years a
new platform replaces the old platform
and the old platform goes away when in
fact the Macintosh was here to stay and
they just weren't treating it that way.
I would say Apple's come full circle now
and views its platforms as institutions
that are there to last decades including
well all of the platforms that they have
including the Mac which started in 1984
but the iPhone certainly iPad you know
even the lesser ones like watch and tvOS
and I think vision OS are things that
they intend to last for decades which at
this point will last well past the
careers of the senior leadership at the
company and I think they have that
mindset but I think they're currently
doing some things and again related to
money just the goddamn money that are
contrary to fostering that but it's this
long-term mindset that the company has
that these platforms are institutions
and that Apple whole is an institution
that is meant to be here for a very long
time And if they don't change, we're or
maybe they don't have to change. I don't
even know.
>> But I think if they don't change, then
when new things come, they become legacy
only, right? They're not going to
disappear. The iPhone's not going
anywhere. But the risk to the company is
that they become legacy only. Maybe like
Microsoft would be if they hadn't moved
to the cloud, right? If Microsoft was
still just about Windows and Office and
stuff like that, where they would be,
they would miss out on the next thing
that their next thing isn't going to
hit. unless they have developer buyin
and that you know that you can easily
disguise that with the ongoing revenue
and profits from those legacy things in
the same way that Microsoft would still
be a very big healthy company even if
they hadn't shifted under Satia Nadella
but they just wouldn't they wouldn't be
number two or number one in the world
right now.
>> Yeah. All right. Well, it's been two and
a half hours. I think we do need to wrap
up. But fascinating conversation. Thank
you so much for your time, John. And
this was
>> Thanks for having me. This was fun. I
really enjoyed it and I hope it's useful
to folks.
>> I won't feel so bad the next time you're
on my show for two hours.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[Music]